<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pope's parliament, containing a pleasant and delightful historie, wherin are ... deliuered ... the paltry trash and trumperies of him and his pelting prelats ... : Whereunto is annexed an Anatomie of Pope Ioane, more apparently opening her whole life and storie. / Written by Iohn Mayo.</title>
            <author>Mayo, John, fl. 1607-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00425</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124300</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">44920370</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 44920370</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173816</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00425)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173816)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2099:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pope's parliament, containing a pleasant and delightful historie, wherin are ... deliuered ... the paltry trash and trumperies of him and his pelting prelats ... : Whereunto is annexed an Anatomie of Pope Ioane, more apparently opening her whole life and storie. / Written by Iohn Mayo.</title>
                  <author>Mayo, John, fl. 1607-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Richard Field dwelling in the Blacke Friers neare Ludgate.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴, G².</note>
                  <note>Title page contains printer's device (McK. 192).</note>
                  <note>"The anatomie of Pope Ioane" (p. [29]-42) has special t.-p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, and with print show-through, and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Joan (Legendary Pope) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173816:1"/>
                  <p>THE POPE'S PARLIAMENT, CONTAINING A PLEASANT AND DELIGHTFVL HISTORIE, WHERIN are throughly deliuered and brightly blazed out, the paltry traſh and trumperies of him and his pelting Prelats, their mutinies, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and diſſentions, their ſtomacke and malice at Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> their f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>fting and foiſting of matters for defence of her, and their Antichriſtian practiſes, for maintenance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> pompe and auarice.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto is annexed an Anatomie of Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly opening her whole life and ſtorie.</p>
                  <p>Written by IOHN MAYO.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Quis tulerit Gracchos de ſeditione querentes?</hi>
                  </q>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                     <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by Richard Field dwelling in the Blacke Friers neare Ludgate. 1591.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173816:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173816:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVL SIR GEORGE TREN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARD KNIGHT, CAPTAINE OF Weymouth Caſtle, and one of the Deputie Lieutenants of the Countie of Dorſet, <hi>Iohn Mayo</hi> wiſheth all increaſe of worſhip and honorable vertues, and at laſt a crowne of eternall glorie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O heart can ſufficiently conceiue, much leſſe anie to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue is able with words to expreſſe, the ſingular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort, ioy and vtilitie, that a Chriſtian hath in this most daungerous pilgrimage,<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.4.</note> in beholding the faire beautie of the Lord, in viſiting his holy Temple, and in learning his dutie towards God, his Prince, and neighbours, according to the mind of the holy Ghoſt expreſſed in the Scriptures. This is of ſuch great weight and importance, that it doth deliuer vs from euerie euill worke,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.18.</note> quencheth all the firie darts of the wicked, checketh and choketh all fickle and tranſitorie vanities, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth glad, cheereth and cheriſheth the conſcience of man in all changes and chaunces of this mortall life whatſoeuer. This is of ſuch ſingular force and operation,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> that it entreth through (as the Apoſtle ſaith) euen vnto the diuiding aſunder of the ſoule, and of the ſpirit, &amp; of the ioynts, and the marrow, purifying our hearts through faith in Chriſt Ieſus, and inſtilling the heauenly drops of his grace into our hard and stonie hearts, to ſouple and ſoften the ſame. This is ſuch a precious balme, &amp; ſoueraigne antidote, that it healeth all our maladies and infirmities, and ſuch a lanterne to our feet and light to our pathes, that it doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from the power of darkneſſe,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> and tranſlateth vs to the kingdome of Christ, putting vpon vs, <hi>vniuerſam illam</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that ſame complete armor of a godly man, that we may ſtand againſt all the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the deuill. O how deare and ſweete was this to that bleſſed king Dauid: how beloued of Saba Queene of Aethiopia: how precious
<pb facs="tcp:173816:3"/>
to Eunuchus,<note place="margin">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 1.5.</note> Cornelius, Eunice Timothies mother, &amp; Lois his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, with many others: and how comfortable and delectable to the Apoſtles, martyrs, and confeſſors. Vanitie is vaine, and all things in the world are but vanitie, beſides the loue of God, and his onely ſeruice.</p>
                  <p>Seeing then, that the word of God is of ſuch efficacie &amp; excellencie, and hath in it ſuch a ſecret and hidden Manna: neceſſarie it is that Man which is borne of a woman, and hath but a ſhort time to liue, ſhould with all humbleneſſe and ſobrietie, read, learne, and inwardly digeſt the ſame, and with diligent ſtudie and contemplation, employ the courſe of his warrefare therein. God made liuing creatures (ſaith Chryſoſtome) for man: but he made man for himſelfe. How for himſelfe? onely to glorifie his name, to ſerue him with feare, and reioyce vnto him with reuerence. He made him after his owne ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and likeneſſe: he gaue him his lawes and commaundements: and therefore he onely ought to giue attendance to them, and to continue in learning of them, that through patience and comfort of them he might haue hope, faith, and immortalitie in Ieſus Chriſt. Euerie one muſt further (as farre foorth as he can) the building of Gods Temple. If he can not bring gold, ſiluer, or precious stones, he muſt bring <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma quae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, pelles, &amp; caprarum pilos,</hi> the leaſt things he hath, skins, and the haires of Goates. We muſt not be idle in Gods great har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, neither ſecure in theſe perillous times: we muſt neuer ceaſe to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and learne, trie out and diſcerne God from Belial, Chriſt from Antichriſt, godly and ſincere doctrine, belonging to the true worſhipping of God, from erronious and damnable tending to ſuperſtition and idolatrie,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4 1.</note> according to that bleſſed ſaying of Saint Iohn: Beleeue not euerie ſpirit, but trie the ſpirits whether they be of God.</p>
                  <p>Theſe reaſons (right Worſhipfull) being weighed and throughly conſidered by me, I was not a little ſpurred and pricked forward ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to take in hand, that might teſtifie and ſhew my zeale and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent affection to the ſame. And by chaunce taking Platina (though a ſhamefull paraſite for the Popes, yet in manie places truly painting and publiſhing their filthineſſe and abominations) I lighted vpon Pope Ioane, of whom he writeth and craftily, cloaketh, in the life of Iohn the eight. Noting the hiſtorie, and perceiuing what a miraculous to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it was ſent of the Lord, to the ſubuerſion of poperie, and to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion of that purple whore: I framed thereupon a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though but a fiction, yet plainly declaring the great choler and
<pb facs="tcp:173816:3"/>
indignation that the Pope and his Prelats haue at the name of Pope Ioane, their palpable blindneſſe, and malcontent ſtomackes, their gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and inſaciable hunger for money, their mutinous diſſenſion and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian practiſes that be among them, and their ſpitefull enuie and enimitie againſt the true profeſſours of the Goſpel: whereunto I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed an anatomie of Pope Ioane, more manifeſtly opening their clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhifts, and excuſes for her, and more apparantly reuealing her whole life and ſtorie.</p>
                  <p>This (right Worſhipfull) I boldly offer vnto you, although it may import ſmall manners and little modeſtie in me: aſſuming ſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your courteſie, as I aſſure my ſelfe you will vouchſafe of my good will and accept of the matter. The matter indeede (I confeſſe) is ſuch, as deſerueth to be handeled of a graue and learned diuine, and can not by reaſon of my ignorance and ſmall knowledge, be ſo cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and clearkely deſcribed, as it ought: yet I doubt not, but it is ſo handled, as you ſhall ſee Pope Ioane painted out in her colours, and behold (as it were) in a glaſſe, the loathſome corruption and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſneſſe of the Romane ſynagogues: howſoeuer it be, I am to craue pardon of skilleſſe attempt, ſhrowding my ſelfe wholy and ſolie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your courteous protection: promiſing, that if hereafter either my wit or skill ſhall be able to yeelde anie better fruite, I will offer it at your Worſhips ſhrine. For you are the Saint to whom in heart I owe moſt dutifull deuotion, being ſuch a lampe and light of iuſtice and good gouernement in this our Countie of Dorſet, ſuch a fautor and friend of vertue and good literature, ſuch a furtherer and fauourer of true Christian religion, and of the preachers and ministers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſo wiſe, well affected, and giuen euerie kind of wayes, that I ſhould rather embeazle, then illuſtrate your condigne prayſe. What godly and Christian orders be obſerued in your houſe? How fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent and forward are you alwayes in her Maieſties ſeruice, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the realme againſt forreine inuaſions, and in detecting and puniſhing thoſe, that wilfullie diſturbe, and ſeeke to ſubuert our happie ſtate and gouernement?<note place="margin">Grafton in the 21. yeere of the reigne of king Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the 7. 1505.</note> Rightly do you aduaunce the great worſhip and credite of your houſe, and truly tread the ſteppes of your famous aunceſtours. For as that noble knight ſir Thomas Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard your grandfather, in the time of king Henrie the ſeuenth, was commended and renowmed, and greatlie thanked of the king
<pb facs="tcp:173816:4"/>
his maister, for receyuing with all humanitie and reuerence, Philip king of Caſtile and Lion, Archduke of Auſtrich and Burgoine, and Earle of Flaunders, who was the kings louing and faithfull friend, and of old familiaritie and acquaintance togither, being driuen by force of weather to the port of Weymouth: ſo your worſhip within theſe few yeares haue beene not a little commended and renowmed, and greatly thanked of her gracious Maieſtie, for nobly entertaining Lewys of Burbon, prince of Condee, being driuen to land at the ſame place. I could vſe further diſcourſes to this effect, but fearing the cenſure of ſmoothing, and hoping you will deine as well of the poore mans mite, as the rich mans treaſure, and ſhadow this my ſlender labour vnder the wings of your tuition, I ſurceaſe any longer to interrupt your ſerious affaires, ſuppliantly crauing of the Almightie, to augment his graces and vertues in you, that after your ſhort pilgrimage here ended, you may reſt with the Iſrael of God, in endleſſe bliſſe and felicitie.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips at commandement, <hi>IOHN MAYO.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173816:4"/>
                  <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Oubtleſſe, thou maiſt maruell, and much miſlike (good cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader) that I, who am but a tender ſuckling, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in good letters, ſhould preſume ſo far, as to take in hand and publiſh that, which I haue rawly and raſhly contriued, being a matter meete and requiſite for a graue and perfect diuine. Certes I cannot altogither excuſe my ſelfe in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe: for I am not ſo blinde, as not to ſee, nor ſo impudent, as not to confeſſe my knowledge to be ſuch, as is fitter to be concealed then reuealed, and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth rather ſilence and reiection, then any affection or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, I am of the mind of learned <hi>Seneca: Malè mihi eſſe malo, quàm molliter.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Seneca. <hi>33.</hi> Epist.</note> I had rather be counted fooliſh and impudent, by offering ſuch ſimple ſtuffe as mine inſufficiency can affoord, then ſlouthfully to ſit ſtill in the market place, and to be neither idle nor well occupied: eſpecially in that matter that might ſhew the daſtardly cowardnes, &amp; baſtardly cauſes of our aduerſaries, who are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered (by reaſon of a few curriſh &amp; curſed ſchiſmatikes of our owne breeding that haue diſturbed our quiet ſtate and gouernment, and troubled not a little many godly and learned men) too much to wallow &amp; welter in their owne loathſome ſecuritie, and to ſleepe (as they ſay) <hi>in vtramuis aurem,</hi> ſoundly and roundly with little or no contradiction. What? <hi>Credimus auectos hostes,</hi> do we thinke that they are gone? Do we beleeue that they are cleane extinct, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate? and that all their treacheries, treaſons, &amp; maſſacres, are dead and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried? No, no, this our ſilence towards them doth breed the more violence in them, and will (I feare) heape greater firebrands of troubles vpon vs. Our owne dangerous and gnawing Vipers (God be thanked) are wel tamed &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently curbed, ſo that they dare not once ſo much as to peep vp their heads. Now let vs haue a vigilant eye, and diligent care to theſe arch-enimies, leaſt they being better armed with fire and ſword, then with the ſcriptures and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, do worke our wo, and make vs buy repentance at too hie a rate. The times were neuer ſo daungerous, as they be now.<note place="margin">Sine pace, Criminatores, Proterui.</note> Men were neuer ſuch <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as they be now: and neuer greater perils were han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ouer our heads. The Pope neuer beſtirred himſelfe more then he doth: the Cardinals, prieſts, monkes, friers, and all the rabblement of them, did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer intend more miſchiefe againſt vs, then they do now. For the ſame Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is practiſed now in Rome among them, that was ſomtime in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel houſe of Epheſus: <hi>Nemo noſtrum frugi esto.</hi> Let no good man be among vs. Therefore let vs look vnto them in time, and beware of their leauen and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſnes, and let me not be too hardly cenſured, becauſe I haue aduentured to offer vnto thee this ſimple Treatiſe called, <hi>The Popes Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> wherin thou maieſt ſee a whole packe of Romiſh trumperies, and Antichriſtian illuſions. Conſtrue well my meaning, and accept my good will: willing by the one, to do thee the beſt good I could, and declaring by the other, my heartie zeale &amp; affection, for the aduancement of Gods true religion, and for the ſuppreſſion of impious ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: howſoeuer thou deeme of it, I am comforted with this. <hi>Tantum emit vidua duobus minutis, quantum emit Petrus, relinquens retia, &amp; quantum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>chaeus dando dimidium patrimonij ſui.</hi> And ſo farewell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine in the Lord IOHN MAYO.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173816:5"/>
                  <head>Candido Lectori. I. O.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VIſne Antichristi vestigia cernere? víſne</l>
                     <l>Romanam praxim cernere? Lector ades.</l>
                     <l>Vis Papae Synodum conflatam mordicùs oestro,</l>
                     <l>Bile, ſupercilijs cernere? Lector ades.</l>
                     <l>Víſne Papistarum diſcrimina, praelia, rixas,</l>
                     <l>Iurgia, praestigias cernere? Lector ades.</l>
                     <l>Vin' tu foemineae contagia dira Iohannae</l>
                     <l>Papae olim Romae cernere? Lector ades.</l>
                     <l>Vin' mores, vitamque ſuam quam turpiter actam,</l>
                     <l>Vin' mortem horrendam cernere? Lector ades.</l>
                     <l>Lector ades, librum hunc eme, perlege, protinus ipſe</l>
                     <l>Haec planè &amp; plenè ſuppeditata feres.</l>
                     <l>Sume ergo placidè, iucundo ſumito vultu,</l>
                     <l>Authori grates pectore redde tuo.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Floridus Mayi est, redolet<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> menſis.</l>
                     <l>Floridus Mayo est, redolet<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> noster.</l>
                     <l>Praebet halantes niueoſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> flores,</l>
                     <l>Alter &amp; alter,</l>
                     <l>Huius ast flores remanent, vigent<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>:</l>
                     <l>Illius flores pereunt, cadunt<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>:</l>
                     <l>Fulgidos veros, rutiloſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> flores</l>
                     <l>Collige lector.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173816:5"/>
                  <head>In commendation of the Author.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SWeete May is come, that winters frost opprest,</l>
                     <l>Whereat the birds their ſiluer notes diſplaies,</l>
                     <l>(As if that Bore as blaſtes had reau'd their rest,</l>
                     <l>And Phoebus rouſde from denne with golden raies,</l>
                     <l>Comes with his ſhining beames, bringing them newes</l>
                     <l>Of weather faire, which as they would enſewes.)</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The May is come that makes the ſhrubs to ſing,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe rubie ſtreames deſcries the ſlow-worms watchs,</l>
                     <l>And Philomela ſits and feares no ſting</l>
                     <l>Of wrath, but quiet naps in rest ſhe catchs.</l>
                     <l>Each bird on toppe of tree with mirth reſounds,</l>
                     <l>Welcome ſweete May, by whom our bliſſe rebounds.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our May, faire knowledge is, error the frost</l>
                     <l>That nipt truthes Laurell boughes and flowers faire,</l>
                     <l>The Protestants the birds that ſorrow lost</l>
                     <l>To ſee vndoubted truth to them repaire:</l>
                     <l>The Philomela ſhewes our noble Queene,</l>
                     <l>The blindfold Pope, the ſlow-worme cloath'd with teene.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>May brings greene buds, blooming with bloſſoms bright,</l>
                     <l>Flora yeelds Poeſies, May yeelds flowers diuine,</l>
                     <l>Surpaſſing May dimming her glittering light:</l>
                     <l>As Sol doth cauſe ſweete Cynthias beames to pine.</l>
                     <l>No labour doth his reaching minde forgoe,</l>
                     <l>Whereby (O Reader good) thy good may grow.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sitting in harbours greene with vertues grace,</l>
                     <l>Not in the chambers of fond Venus lust:</l>
                     <l>He meanes to make his pen iourney apace,</l>
                     <l>To ſhew the truth, and rub off errors rust.</l>
                     <l>Then hither youth repaire with Echoes laude,</l>
                     <l>Giue May due thankes, his praiſe deſeru'd applaud.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Robert Foord.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173816:6"/>
                  <head>THE ARGVMENT OF THIS TREATISE.</head>
                  <p>THe Pope goeth in his ſolemne proceſſion: by the aduiſe of Cardinall <hi>Allen</hi> he paſſed through that ſtreete, where the Marble image of the woman Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> was erected, and yet ſtandeth, repreſenting her filthineſſe and abhomination: he loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vpon it, and with the ſight thereof is ſo ſtrangly afrighted, that he ran backe againe like a mad man, to the great admiration of the people. The next day he called his Cardinals, and held a Parliament in his Conſiſtorie: where three queſtions were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded &amp; agreed vpon. The hollow chaire of Porphirie ſtone, vſed for the proofe of the Popes humanitie, was torne in peeces. The Marble image of the woman Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> was broken down, and all the Engliſh catholikes were exiled and commanded to packe out of Rome the next day. They ſeeing the Popes holy diſpleaſure againſt them, concluded togither to giue him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Florens, and euerie yeere after ſo much, if ſo be that they might haue his bleſſed fauour and permiſſion to abide in Rome: whereupon the Pope abſolueth and recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them, and taketh them into his gracious liking againe.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173816:6"/>
                  <head>THE POPES PARLIAMENT.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Regorie</hi> the fourtéenth, now Pope of Rome,<note place="margin">Franciſcus Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabella. Papa facit quicquid libet, etiam illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cita: &amp; est plus quàm Deus.</note> 
                     <hi>no meere naturall man, but Lord of Lords, and king of kings, and more then God,</hi> as his adherents are blindly perſwaded: after he had ſate in the chaire of Porphirie ſtone, of ſome called the chaire of eaſe, or hollow ſtoole of eaſement, for proofe of his humanitie: mounted vp aloft in his gaudie Pontificalibus, and paſſing in his ſolemne proceſſion, from S. <hi>Peters</hi> church to <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane,</hi> by the meanes of Cardinall <hi>Allen</hi> an Engliſh fugitiue, a man much fauoured and fancied of the Pope and his prelats, he tooke his way ſtraight forth, and did not paſſe vndirectly by other ſtreetes (making his way ſomwhat the longer) as his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours haue vſed to do, for the ſpace of <hi>500.</hi> yéeres and more: where by the way he ſaw the marble image of the woman Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> lying in trauel, who going that way, ſtreined with pains, betwéene Coloſſeo, and S. <hi>Clemens</hi> church brought forth &amp; died, and (as they ſay) was there buried. Looking vpon the image, and noting the faſhion, proportion, and prodigie of the ſame,<note place="margin">A ſtraunge thing, in ſuch an earthly God, ſurely.</note> he was vpon the ſodaine aſtonied, and as one bereft of his wits: in ſo much, that in a great chafe and furie, throwing off his Myter, caſting away his Pixe, regarding neither his pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificals, nor proceſſion, he ſhooke vp his old crooked ioyntes, and ran backe againe, as faſt as his heeles could fling, to his Pallace, leauing behinde him the Cardinals, biſhops, prieſtes, and all the reſt of the people.</p>
                  <p>Strange was the ſight, and rare was the accident, that he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:173816:7"/>
which is equall with the Patriarks,<note place="margin">This is the blind opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites.</note> aboue kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and one that is al, and aboue all, that cannot erre by any meanes poſſible, ſhould haue ſuch a foule blot to his holineſſe, as not to remember himſelfe, as though he had dranke of the riuer <hi>Lethe</hi> in hell, <hi>Quae praeteritarum rerum fertur obliuionem indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere:</hi> and ſo to runne and rage, as though the water of the lakes in Ethiope had béene in his belly:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ouid. Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morp.</hi> 15. 197.</note> 
                     <hi>Quos ſi quis faucibus hauſit, Aut furit, aut patitur mirum grauitate ſoporem.</hi> Yea, it was ſuch a ſupernaturall euent and aſpect, as the beholders thereof, and all they that heard of it, did deſcant diuerſly vpon it, and were ſtroken into no ſmall admiration therewith. Some ſaid, he had a celeſtiall motion in him, and feared, leſt he ſhould be taken vp into heauen,<note place="margin">Plut. in vita Romuli.</note> as <hi>Romulus</hi> was. Some ſaid, he was verie ill at eaſe, &amp; doubted leſt dirges ſhould be ſung for his ſoule the next day.<note place="margin">Ben. Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis.</note> Some ſaid, he had the ſpirite of <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> who being but Cardinall, did beate Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> with his fiſt, and kept him priſoner. Some ſaid, the marble image was the cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and wiſhed it had neuer béene there erected. Some laid all the blame vpon Cardinall <hi>Allen,</hi> the Popes ſwéete dearling, &amp; ſaid, that he was worthy to haue ſharpe and ſeuere puniſhment for it. Some alſo led with a better ſpirite then the reſt, ſaid, that the Pope ſurely was Antichriſt that man of ſin,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.4.</note> ſitting in the church of God, &amp; ſhewing himſelfe aboue all that is worſhiped or called God, &amp; that this was a moſt liuely &amp; manifeſt toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, ſhewed of God, to the confuſion &amp; ouerthrowing of that beaſt. But Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Allen</hi> (good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) was more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the reſt,<note place="margin">Cardinal Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle grieued with the Popes miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune.</note> not a little terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied &amp; tottered with this chance, yea, he was ſo nipt in the pate, &amp; ſtroken with ſuch a paralyticall paſſion, that his Cardinals hat would ſcarſe abide vpon his ſhauen crowne. Wherfore he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew himſelfe from the companie, &amp; with al ſpéed he could, went to his lodging, &amp; there locking himſelf faſt into his ſtudy, he mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; ruminated vpon the matter, &amp; at laſt fel into theſe ſpéeches with himſelfe.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Now muſt I néeds beléeue, that all things worke vnto good, vnto them that be in Chriſt Ieſus: and that truth wil conquer falſhood, though it be neuer ſo finely or freſhly coloured. Now muſt I perforce confeſſe, though neuer ſo vnwillingly, that the truth of God is mighty, &amp; ſhal preuaile: that if the God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173816:7"/>
come into the Temple,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 5.</note> the idoll of <hi>Dagon</hi> muſt néedes fall downe: that darkenes ſhall flie before the light: and the more fiercely mans wiſdome ſhall withſtand, the more glorious ſhall God be in his victorie. Now alas muſt I affirme that, which erſt I haue vehemently and vauntingly denied, that Rome is the great citie of Babylon, that the Pope is Antichriſt, that ſon of perdition, and that the Romane Church is the verie ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Sathan. For what maruellous miracles hath God ſhewed, that he is highly diſpleaſed and offended at vs? What ſtrange ſignes and tokens, that he abhorreth and abandoneth our religion, and the profeſſors therof?<note place="margin">Eſay. 30.</note> What liuely and plaine demonſtrations, that we are children of vntruth, children that will not heare the law of God? Is <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour, Chriſts vicar, the ſhepheard of the vniuerſall Church, now an <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> and an enemie to God? Is our Catholique, Apoſtolique, auten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, and mother Church, become an harlot, corrupt and putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied? Are all our ornaments, orders, and ceremonies, but toies, traſh, and trumperies? all our Saints and pictures, but dumbe ſtockes and foolerie? all our pompe, pride, and prodigalitie, contemptible and odious? Is our antiquitie, our vniuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and vnitie, whereupon we haue bragged and boaſted ſo exceedingly, now vilified, deteſtable, and nothing worth? And are our images heatheniſh, but ſiluer &amp; gold,<note place="margin">Pſal. 135.</note> the works of mens hands? Haue they mouthes, and ſpeake not, eyes and ſee not, eares, and heare not? And are all we like vnto them, that put our truſt in them? VVhy then, <hi>viciſti Galilaee;</hi> take all, and pay the Baker. Thou knoweſt thine owne, and no power can pull them out of thine hand.</p>
                  <p>But ſoft &amp; faire man, <hi>Sic notus Vliſſes?</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne not ſo haſtily, for, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; temeritie is da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in all matters. <hi>Conſulta quae ſunt agenda, cuncta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tèr. <hi>Take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in thoſe things which thou doeſt.</hi>
                     </hi> Thinke with thy ſelfe, Rome is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Rome is Rome, ſtrength, power and health, the Metropolitane of all Europe, the rocke of Chriſt, the ſpouſe of Chriſt, the light of the whole world, &amp; cannot with one ſmall earthquake be ſhaken and ouerthrowne. Our Pope is Chriſts vice-gerent, the head of all Churches, the prince of Paſtours,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:173816:8"/>
and as farre aboue kings, as God is aboue man. He hath the keyes of heauen, the triple crowne, both ſwords, authoritie ouer heauen and hell, to let &amp; ſet, bind and looſe, and do what pleaſe him, and cannot with one bare miſchance be harmed or diſcredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.<note place="margin">Note the braue and luſty ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of a ſtout papiſt.</note> Nay, he hath wealth and riches, treaſure &amp; iewels, and what not: and is farre happier &amp; better then <hi>Peter</hi> was, who ſaid, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; argentum non eſt mihi, <hi>Siluer and gold I haue none.</hi>
                     </hi> What is there then that can diminiſh his glorie, cracke his credite, or impaire his holineſſe? <hi>An ſemper feriet quodcún<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> minabitur arcus?</hi> Will euerie bow that is bent ſtrike the marke? And euery little blaſt ſubuert the Roman faith? No, no, it is farre otherwiſe. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that the Popes heretofere haue had as badde, or rather worſe chances then this, and yet there was no contradiction to them, nor any derogation to their religion. Remember the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Pope <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> of <hi>Clement</hi> the eight, of <hi>Innocentius</hi> the third. Remember the opinions of <hi>Iohn 22.</hi> of <hi>Liberius,</hi> &amp; many others.<note place="margin">I channe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus de illuſtr. ſcrip. Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>an.</note> Remember the madge Howlet, that ſate vpon the middle beame of ſaint <hi>Martins</hi> Temple, two dayes together: where the Pope called <hi>Balthaſar,</hi> with his prelates, ſate in councell, flickering about with his ſhreeching noiſe, and caſting his broad eyes directly vpon <hi>Balthaſar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m 1. fol. 705. &amp; 706.</note> who would not be beaten away with libets, or clubbes, or crying noiſe, till with much cudgel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at him, being ſore beaten, he fell downe dead before them all. Remember alſo the ſtraunge ſights, the monſtrous births, and the ſignes in the elements, that haue beene in Rome. and in other Countreys, where the Romane faith is profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. What for all this? Is our Pope preiudiced, or his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe abhorred? Is our religion changed, our pompe diminiſhed, our orders diſſolued, or anie one iote of our ceremonies abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?<note place="margin">O worthie proctour for the pope.</note> No, no, the Pope is too mightie to haue repulſe of earthly creatures: and Rome is too ſtrong to be blowne downe with ſo light a blaſt: <hi>Hic Petrus, haec Petra:</hi> Here is the faith: here is the way. And if an Angell come from heauen, and tell the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, <hi>Anathema,</hi> we will not beleeue him. Well, well: but <hi>conſilium domi:</hi> take counſaile and aduiſement with thy ſelfe, and catch not ſo fooliſhly at the Moone-ſhine in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Conſider yet further of the matter, and thou ſhalt not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:173816:8"/>
ſo lightly ſlippe it ouer. The Pope was ſtraungely afrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. No ſmall matter. Where? in his ſolemne proceſſion. A ſhrewed peece of worke. How came it to paſſe? by beholding the marble image of Pope <hi>Ioane.</hi> O this is gall to me,<note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſed the Pope to paſſe throgh the forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtreete.</note> and worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood to Engliſh Catholiques. But how did it chance, that he had not refrained that way, as the Popes manner hath a long whiles beene? O it was by my meanes, <hi>conſcientia mille teſtes.</hi> I cannot, nor may not denie it. I neuer thought any ſuch thing would haue happened vnto him: yea I thought, the refraining of the Popes that way to haue beeae cauſeleſſe, and but méere vanitie. How ſhall I pacifie this tumult? How ſhall I pull my necke out of this coller? With what face ſhall I looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reuerend holineſſe of <hi>Gregorie?</hi> What opinion will he now conceiue of me, that hath loued me tenderly, fauoured me eſpecially, and honourablie promoted me to the dignitie of a Cardinall? And what will he thinke alſo of my good country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whom he harboureth, ſuccoureth, and maintaineth at his great charges? <hi>Veh miſero mihi, quanta de ſpe decidi.</hi> I was neuer in this extremitie, and I neuer kindled ſuch firebrandes of troubles before. Shall I flie? that would be a moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſcredite. Shall I hide away? that is daſtardly Shal I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the fault? that ſauours of baſe ſimplicitie.<note place="margin">See the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion.</note> Shall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, and haſten backe againe to my natiue Countrey? what? thinke not of that: be rather thine owne butcher. Shall I beare a bolde face, and manly reſolution, and feare no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours? Oh this is the way: <hi>Hic labor, hoc opus, eſt:</hi> here goeth the hare away. Procéede and feare not. Thou art a Cardinall:<note place="margin">O noble courage in a cardinal, and worthie acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for him.</note> thou haſt cunning to ſmooth, Logicke to reaſon, eloquence to perſwade, yea and Magicke too, if neede be, to worke greater miracles then theſe.</p>
                  <q>Flectere ſi nequeo Superos, Acheronta mouebo.</q>
                  <p>Therefore proface, and ſtint not: <hi>Audentes fortuna iuuat:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eneid.</hi> 7.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune fauours them that be reſolute.</p>
                  <p>Hauing thus ſpoken, he left his cloſet, and went towards <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane</hi> the Popes pallace, following the counſell of <hi>Aeneas: <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ingentibus aeger.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Spem vultu ſineulat, premit altum corde dolorem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eneid.</hi> 1.</note> bearing a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173816:9"/>
faire face outwardly, but inwardly pinched with manie bitter paſſions, and millions of griefes: and comming into the Popes court, as he had beene accuſtomed, was noted and maligned at by many, yea verie heardly and heauily taken: yet he went for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, not forgetting <hi>Didoes</hi> leſſon:
<q>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ineid.</hi> 4.</note>Degeneres animos timor arguit:</q>
And hied to the ſwéete ſide of his good Lord and maſter the Pope: fully determining to trie the vttermoſt of the chauece, and what would befall vnto him. He found the Pope (as his good lucke was) in reaſonable good temper, and recouered of his former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonie:<note place="margin">The great ſtudie of the Pope that he vſeth.</note> yet neither occupied in the pulpit (I warrant you) nor in the ſtudie of Theologie, nor feeding his ſhéepe, as Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded <hi>Peter.</hi> But how? he was with ſome of his Cardinals and other his eſpeciall friends at dinner, where all things were <hi>lautè</hi> and <hi>opiparè,</hi> fine and curious: where no daintie cates and delicates were wanting, both deare bought, and farre brought, and good for ladies.<note place="margin">Another great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance that the pope had.</note> The Pope he ſo glutted and greaſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with good chéere, that his holineſſe was ſomewhat plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and in the ſame mood that the Poet <hi>Ennius</hi> was when he could beſt verſifie: inſomuch, that ſéeing Cardinall <hi>Allen</hi> doing his ghoſtly dutie vnto him, he ſpake after this maner. VVhat Cardinall <hi>Allen?</hi> you are welcom, come ſit downe with vs, <hi>Qui é aſſai con che.</hi> Here is good chéere. Theſe words did not pleaſe a little the Cardinall: they were honie to his mouth, Nectar to his heart, and heauenly harmonie to his eares: ſo that without further entreaty, he ſate down with them, &amp; fed as hardly &amp; hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly,<note place="margin">For all their boaſting of their vnitie they quarrel one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and differ in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</note> as ſuch a paſſionate man could do. The reſt of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, not forgetting the late ſtrange euent, did lowre &amp; looked ſowre vpon the Cardinall, murmuring and muttering at him not a little: yet fearing the Popes deitie, and reſpecting the high dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of his triple crowne, they cloaked and coloured ſome hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie towards him, and vſed the beſt affabilitie they could. After they had well taken their repaſt, and talked ſomewhat merily of pretie paſtimes and daliances:<note place="margin">The table talke of the Papiſts, of daliance.</note> the Pope rouzed from a ſwéet lullabie, eleuating his head with a higher Catholike a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect then before, began to fixe and caſt his eyes vpon Cardinall <hi>Allen:</hi> and after he had rubbed a little with his hallowed hands,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173816:9"/>
he fell into ſome memorie with himſelfe, &amp; gaue to the Cardinal an other welcome, after this maner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cardinale, voi non mangiate, vi vergognate? <hi>Cardinall, you eate nothing, are you aſhamed?</hi>
                     </hi> If you are, it is a ſigne of ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, and vnacquainted paſſion in you: this was not wont to be your faſhion. The Cardinall with all reuerence and ſubmiſſion vnto him, thus replied. <hi>Io ho beue mangiato,</hi> I thanke your holineſſe, I was neuer yet aſhamed to take my meate: and it ſhall be a great alteration and paſſion that ſhall make me leaue and loath it. Well, well (ſayde the Pope) I know what I know, and you know who I am. <hi>Nimia familiaritas parit contemptum,</hi> I haue loued you too well,<note place="margin">The Pope repenteth of the great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour that he ſhewed to the Cardinall.</note> yea I would I had not loued you ſo well, for then I had not beene loued ſo ill. The Cardinall anſwered, Your holineſſe may déeme of me as you pleaſe, and ſpeake of me what you liſt, I may not, nor ought not gaineſay you, <hi>ſub poena mortalis peccati:</hi> vnder paine of mortall ſinne. But if once I ſhould be found not lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing you, or anie kinde of wayes miſconſtruing of your excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie: well may I thinke that I breathed, but neuer that I li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. <hi>Decipimar ſpecie</hi> (quoth the Pope) there is knauerie in your budget, and I ſée now which way ſhe wind bloweth, I haue followed your humour too much, and I haue had too great truſt and confidence to you Engliſh aliants: for you haue brought more diſcredite to my Sea, more troubles to my ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and more charges to my holineſſe, then any other nation whatſoeuer: and this you ſhall ſhortly know more at large, to your bad digeſtion. The Cardinall would haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto him againe, but the companie would not permit him: inſomuch, that he departed away with a buzzing flie in his eare, more troubling him then before. The Cardinall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing departed, the Pope proſecuted the matter.<note place="margin">The Pope exclaimeth againſt the Cardinall &amp; his countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> Sure I am (moſt noble Cardinals) that you maruell not a little where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I reprehended and accuſed Cardinall <hi>Allen</hi> ſo openly, and dealt ſo roundly and ſoundly with him, as plainly to tell him of his offence, and duly and truely to conuince him of his treacherie. Aſſure your ſelues, cauſe I haue to do it, yea and ſuch cauſe, as grieueth and girdeth me to the quicke.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173816:10"/>
For I haue found him ſuch a péeuiſh paraſite, and couſoning <hi>quondam</hi> to me his Lord, and high Biſhop, ſuch a poyſoned ſtaine and blemiſh to you his fellow Cardinals, and ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe and downefall to our Catholique Church, that hee is worthie, not onely preſently to be baniſhed from our Court, but alſo to be afflicted with a farre greater puniſhment. Now I know the ſcuruie ſycophant, and the paltrie peaſant, <hi>tanquam Corui pullos ſuos.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Fit words for a Pope.</note> Now the beggerly route and rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blement of Engliſh miſcreants, haue caſt off their maſkes and viſardes, and ſhewen themſelues to be flatterers, picke-thankes, and cogging clawbackes. Wherefore I proteſt and ſweare vnto you by my holineſſe, that they are eyeſores and vlcers vnto me, and ſhall not from hencefoorth come into my ſacred fauour and acceptation. Yea I tell you (my Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals) that I will haue them cleane extirpate and exiled out of all my territories, dominions and prouinces, or elſe I will loſe my triple Diademe and ſcepter.<note place="margin">The Pope comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth a parliament</note> I commaund you therefore vpon your oath, and obedience to our holy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church, and to me your high Lord, and ſupreame paſtour, that you, and all the reſt of the Cardinals, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to morrow in my conſiſtorie, by nine of the clocke in the forenoone, and eſpecially Cardinall <hi>Allen</hi> that Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh runne-away, there to anſwere ſuch things as ſhall be obiected agaynſt him. The Cardinals hearing the holie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers commaundement, forthwith did execute the ſame, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding worde to the reſt of the Cardinals, and principallie to Cardinall <hi>Allen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cardinall Allen hardly delt withall.</note> cauſing his lodging to be watched all that night for feare, leaſt he ſhould priuily eſcape away. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Allen</hi> now percyuing how much the fire was kindled, and what a manie of ſtinging hornets hee had ſtirred vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, was ſo perplexed and peſtered, that he reſted, <hi>a la mort,</hi> fit for nothing but for a dumbe ſhadow: yet ſcanning the matter more indifferently, and weighing alſo his owne worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vocation more exactly, he did ſomewhat mittigate his griefe, and confirme his heart: ſo that with care-away and chaunce what may, he was this pleaſaunt with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:173816:10"/>Tuſh man, all is well inough, if thou canſt be content:<note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</note> let care be the leaſt thoughe of a thouſand. Can one petie miſfortune, or one little fleabiting diſgrace thy holineſſe, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beazle thy fame, and ſacke thy credite, illuſtrate to all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques in Europe? No, no: if thou thinkeſt ſo, thou art farre beſides the cuſhion, and doeſt ſhew thy ſelfe to be a boy, and a milkeſoppe, vnworthie of thy name and dignitie. For maugre the holy father <hi>Gregorie</hi> himſelfe, maugre the Cardinals, and maugre al the potentates of the court of Rome, thou canſt not be once cloyed, or annoyed, or ſo much as driuen to <hi>a non plus</hi> in the matter. Thou canſt ſmooth and ſooth,<note place="margin">Theſe be the fruites of Papiſts.</note> thou canſt with the Satyre out of one mouth blow both whotte and colde: thou knoweſt well enough the faſhion and frailtie of this Court,<note place="margin">Omnia Roma cum precio.</note> thou haſt <hi>vnguentum rubrum</hi> to greaſe them withall if néede bee: thou haſt enough, and enough, to pacifie this fray, and to ſaue thy ſelfe harmeleſſe. Therefore be not diſmayde: <hi>ſat ſupérque habes:</hi> and ſay with <hi>Niobe: <hi>tutum me copia fecit.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hauing thus ſpoken, he went vp and downe with a pleaſant and merrie countenaunce, couering as well as he could, all his griping griefes and patheticall affections, with an outward colour of great courage, ſpirite and ſecuritie. Yet by no meanes he could driue away the cogitation out of his heart, but euer he hammered and hacked vpon it, and eſpecially how he ſhould the next day anſwere the matter brought in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. Therefore he diſputed <hi>pro &amp; con,</hi> with himſelfe: and armed his heade ſo ſtrongly, and bombaſted his braines ſo egregiouſlie, that his force ſeemed impregnable, and hee thought himſelfe able, in diſputation to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with the beſt doctour, and profoundeſt <hi>Coriphaeus</hi> in all Italie.</p>
                  <p>Well, the day and hower was come, wherein he ſhould draw néere towardes the Conſiſtorie, wherefore he got all his tackling and furniture about him, and went his way. As ſoone as hee, and the reſt of the Cardinals were ſate, the mightie Maieſtie of the high potentate <hi>Gregorie</hi> came in, glittering and gliſtering in his pontificall and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173816:11"/>
princely robes, fortified with no ſmal companie of men and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraies,<note place="margin">Plaine and euident to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</note> and ſat downe in a ſtately and emperiall chaire there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and prepared for him: after that he had well ſetled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he began this ſolemne oration.</p>
                  <p>(Reuerend Cardinals) my owne déere and firſt begotten children,<note place="margin">The Popes oration.</note> fit and worthie paſtours of my Catholique and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church: may it pleaſe you, to the health and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of my authoritie to the praiſe and honor of God,<note place="margin">See his pride and ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: he putteth himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</note> and to the encreaſe and aduancement of our Romane faith and religion, to conſider with me, and to iudge vprightly of theſe three points following.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, whether the Porphyrie chaire, vſed for the triall and proofe of our virility,<note place="margin">The points to be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Parliament.</note> is to be preſerued as hitherto it hath bene, or elſe to be deſtroyed and aboliſhed.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, whether the marble image néere Coloſſeo, that ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> lying in her trauell, is to be kept as an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent monument, or to be defaced and broken in péeces, as a ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous and odious ſpectacle.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, whether the Engliſh fugitiues are to be retained, and further maintained at our great charges, or elſe without any longer delay, to be vtterly expelled, and exiled.</p>
                  <p>They all anſwered, it pleaſeth vs. The Pope then went for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on this maner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The popes iudgement in the firſt point.</note>(Moſt noble Cardinals) I will firſt of all relate vnto you my ſacred and Apoſtolicall cenſure, concerning theſe queſtions, and then I will permit you franckly and fréely to propoſe your iudgements alſo. My cenſure concerning the hollow chaire of Porphirie ſtone, is affirmatiue, and this: that it is no longer to be kept and preſerued, as proper to the Romane chaire of bleſſed <hi>Peter,</hi> prince of the Apoſtles, but forthwith to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced and deſtryed, as a thing too baſe and contemptible, far vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie of our high calling, and reuerend iuriſdiction. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that moue me are theſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, it is no ſmall defamation and diſgrace to Chriſt his chiefe vicar and paſtour, to him whoſe power is diuine and emperious, farre aboue any mortall man, to yéeld
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173816:11"/>
himſelfe to ſo vnſéemely and vile athing,<note place="margin">Sabellicus, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neadis. <hi>9.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> ab vltimo Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cono attrectan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> as to ſuffer another man <hi>attrectare genitalia</hi> at his creation.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is a renouation, and continuall demonſtration of the memorie of Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> who hath brought more infamie, contempt, and deteſtation, to our ſanctified chaire and religion, then now can, or euer (I feare me) will be well wiped, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away. Thirdly, the defacing and aboliſhing of it, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine hereticall and contumelious tongues, aſwage the cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of theſe our times, quiet the controuerſies of religion, and reſtore a more true and Eccleſiaſticall peace vnto vs. Now let me heare what your opinion is. <hi>Conuenimus omnes,</hi> ſaid the Cardinals: your holineſſe hath ſpoken nothing, but that which is for the glorie of the bleſſed chaire of <hi>Peter,</hi> for the benefite of the ancient &amp; Catholike faith, and for the aſſurance of our ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and dignities. And what ſay you Cardinall <hi>Allen,</hi> quoth the Pope? <hi>Vox tua rauceſcit?</hi> are you mute and ſilent? How like you theſe ſuppoſitions? The Cardinall with all mildneſſe and modeſtie, thus anſwered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conuenimus omnes.</hi> We agrée altogither, they are pure and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, fit and famous decrees and canons, for your Apoſtolical ſeate, and for the ancient, abſolute, and full perfect faith of the high citie of Rome. <hi>Perge, perge,</hi> go on, go on, quoth the Pope, you haue more to ſay I am ſure.</p>
                  <p>Since it ſo pleaſeth your ſanctimonie (ſaid the Cardinall) <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentiſſimè pergam,</hi> I will go forward with all my heart. Right well, may I vſe the words of the learned father S. <hi>Hierome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In Epist.</note> 
                     <hi>Haec eſt fides (beatiſſime Papa) quam in catholica diſcimus Eccleſia, in qua ſi minùs peritè aut parùm cautè, forte aliquid poſitum est, emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dari cupimus à te, qui Petri fidem &amp; ſedem tenes. <hi>This is the faith (ô moſt bleſſed father) which we learne in the catholike Church: wherein if any thing peraduenture be put not skilfully nor adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly, we deſire to be reformed of you, who vſurpe the ſeate and faith of Peter.</hi>
                     </hi> For if the holy mother church of Rome,<note place="margin">Falſe &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> be ſo foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, built, and grounded vpon <hi>Peter,</hi> Prince of the Apoſtles, that the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it: and if <hi>Peters</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour and Chriſts chiefe ſteward, hath the keyes of heauen gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him, to binde and looſe, to adde and ſubtract, to multiplie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173816:12"/>
and diuide at his celeſtiall will and pleaſure: then who may vnder paine of damnation gaineſay his heauenly ſentence and opinion, and without his great curſe and thundering bull, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate any one iot from his faith and religion.<note place="margin">A notable Paraſite.</note> If your omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent authoritie (moſt gracious father) be as farre aboue Princes and Emperours, as the ſunne is aboue the moone, and aboue the Angels of God, without whom there is no ſaluation: then how may we, or dare we once ſpurne or maligne at you, and reiect your diuine and infallible ſentence, in any matter whatſoeuer? You are the ſpirituall man that iudgeth all things, &amp; you your ſelfe are iudged of none: and although you be found vnprofitable, and remiſſe in your workes, hauing no regard to your owne ſaluation,<note place="margin">This was the deteſtable doctrine of Pope Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh man.</note> nor to the ſaluation of your brethren, ſo that you lead with your ſelfe innumerable heapes of people, vnto the chiefeſt bondſlaue of hell, there euer to be beaten with manie ſtripes: yet your faultes no mortall man preſumeth to reprooue here, becauſe you ſhall iudge all men, and be iudged of no man your ſelfe. Then your good and ſacred cenſure of the Porphirie ſtone, (my moſt high Lord, and reuerend father) is of vs all to be adored and honoured, eſpecially, ſince it is grounded vpon moſt weightie and ſubſtantiall reaſons, tending not a little to the health and illuſtration of the holy church of Rome, and to the aduancement and propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your ſplendent light and prehemence. For certes, in euerie indifferent mans iudgement, the preſeruation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is in no kind of way a glorie and furtherance, but euerie kind of way a ſcandale and ignomie, to the Catholike religion, and to the principall towre thereof the citie of Rome. What doubt can there be in the humanitie of the high biſhop that is to be created? Can hée bée <hi>Hermophroditus,</hi> a man and a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,<note place="margin">It is poſſible: for Semyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis being a woman, was a long time taken for a man.</note> both in one? Is it poſſible that a woman being not capeable of holie orders, can aſpire vnto that dignitie, and be founde worthy of that high calling and function, in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, grauitie, learning, wit, and authoritie? or is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that a woman can ſo long conceale her ſexe, and not be knowne and eſpied? Surely, ſurely, the kéeping of the hollow chaire of Porphirie ſtone, and the ſitting therein of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:173816:12"/>
our Lord and high biſhop, is of all other things moſt vaine, fooliſh, and ridiculous, ſauouring of little wit, and leſſe wiſedome. Notwithſtanding ſome there be,<note place="margin">A fooliſh ſhadowing &amp; friuolous.</note> that ſhadow the matter, and affirme that the ſtoole of naturall eaſement, doth ſerue for this purpoſe to the Pope, leaſt the ſoueraigntie of honour exhibited vnto him, ſhould in his owne conceite lift him higher, then for the degrée of humaine condition: but this is to little or no purpoſe: therefore <hi>Dirue, confunde,</hi> downe with it, and teare it in péeces: <hi>Conuenimus omnes,</hi> We all agrée to it: let not ſo vile an obiect remaine in your court, and ſuch a peſtiferous cuſtome of diſgrace and raſcalitie be anie lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vſed of <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſours.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gregorie,</hi> ſéeing the Cardinall ſo vehement and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant in the cauſe, brake off his ſpéech, and ſaid, <hi>Satis loquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> you haue ſpoken enough: the matter is more clearer then the noone day, and néede no farther diſputation.<note place="margin">
                        <p>The Popes commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Porphirie chaire.</p>
                        <p>The Porphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie chaire is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Conſiſtorie.</p>
                     </note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my pleaſure and commaundement is this: that the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phirie chaire be preſently brought hither into the Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie before vs, and be in our ſight broken, defaced, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly aboliſhed. The Cardinals hearing theſe words, ſent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly for it, and ſoone it was brought into the Conſiſtorie, and before the face of the Pope and his Cardinals, all hewed and ſhiuered into péeces: when this was done, the Pope procéeded after this manner.</p>
                  <p>(Moſt worthy Cardinals) ſéeing that we haue fully and abſolutely conſidered and decided the firſt point, and brought it to that effect, as is lawfull and expedient for vs: let vs come likewiſe to the ſecond, which is: whether the marble image by the Coloſſeo, repreſenting the woman Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> in childe bearing, is to be kept, and let ſtande, as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it hath béene, or elſe vtterly to bée defaced and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. My cenſure is in like manner as it was of the former,<note place="margin">The Popes cenſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the marble image.</note> that it is wholly and principally to be ſubuerted and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: for it is more to be feared then the Baſiliſke, and more to be auoided then the Cockatrice: and it is a greater ſtaine, hurt, and reproch to our ſeate Apoſtolike, a more manifeſt preſident and picture of the woman Pope, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173816:13"/>
a more grieuous eye-ſore to a Catholike,<note place="margin">The Popes weighty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of it</note> then the other: this is publike and openly to be ſeene, whereas the other is ſecret and cloſely kept: this is eaſily to be perceiued of euerie one that ſéeth it, the vſe of the other is hardly to be vnderſtood of any: yea, this is the bodie and verie heart of Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> but the other is but a little part and member thereof. I maruell much, what he ment that firſt cauſed it to be erected, and what my predeceſſours ment to let it ſtand in that place as it doth. What ſay you to it renowmed Cardinals?</p>
                  <p>Cardinall <hi>Medices,</hi> a man of the greateſt wealth and riches, though not of the greateſt wit and learning, made this aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
                  <p>Nothing is or hath béene (moſt ſoueraigne Lord, and ſupreme Paſtour) that more impaireth the excellencie of your ſacred ſcepter, more eclipſeth the orient beames of your dignitie, and more abrogateth the rites and canons of the auncient and catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Romaine religion, then that fond and fooliſh fable of Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> which our aduerſaries beléeue as an infallible truth, and moſt vſually caſt vs in the téeth withall, aboue all other things. What meanes haue heretofore béene vſed for the remedie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, you are not ignorant: the whole ſtorie hath béene ſtoutly and ſtifly denied, and yet it auaileth not. Her name hath béene left out of the Calender of the Popes, and yet nothing the better. <hi>Onuphrius Pamuinius</hi> of ſet purpoſe hath béene hired to face out this matter,<note place="margin">Truth it is, he wrote worthily for his hire, win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſome credite, by aduenturing his wits in a deſperate cauſe.</note> and yet it is neuer the néere. But this way propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by your highnes, is of farre greater force and excellency, and of ſuch ſingular weight &amp; importance, that néeds it muſt ſlacke and qualifie the ſlaunder, and verie ſhortly burie the memorie thereof in perpetual obliuion. For the hollow Porphirie ſtone, and that vaine and vile image being gone, what remaineth to continue the remembrance thereof? Who can miſlike this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe? Who ought to reprehend this prouiſo? Nay who dare reſiſt ſuch a worthie and apoſtolicall action?<note place="margin">A parls page for the Pope.</note> Then let it forthwith be executed, (moſt holy Lord) and let not the matter, that wil be ſuch a light and lampe to the Catholike faith, be any longer ſtayed or delaied. Are you al of this mind (ſaid the Pope?) The Cardinals with one conſent anſwered. <hi>Verum eſt, ſaluberri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173816:13"/>
est, nemo nostrum refragatur.</hi> It is true,<note place="margin">
                        <p>The Popes iudgement concerning the marble image.</p>
                        <p>The marble image is brought into the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie.</p>
                        <p>It is broken into pieces, and throwne into Tyber, togither with the Porphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſtone.</p>
                     </note> it is good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom counſell, none of vs do withſtand it. Then (quoth the Pope) let it forthwith be ſet vpon: let the image be broken downe, and no one péece thereof left behind. Let it be brought hither before vs into the Conſiſtorie that we may ſée it defaced, and not be deceiued in the doing of it. When the Pope had thus ſpoken, men were preſently ſent to breake it downe, and to bring it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them in the Conſiſtorie, which they quickly diſpatched, and did accordingly. When the Pope ſaw it, he ſaid: ſtrike it, batter it, breake it in péeces like a potters veſſell, and caſt it into Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber togither with the Porphirie ſtone: which was immediatly done, according to his gracious will and commandement.</p>
                  <p>This being done the Pope ſaid to the Cardinals: it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth now, that we come vnto the third and laſt point: but the time is paſt, and therefore we will omit it till the afternoone: I commaund you therefore vpon your fealtie and obedience to <hi>Peters</hi> chaire, to our mother church, and to the catholike and Apoſtolike faith, that you faile not to appeare héere againe in the afternoone by two of the clocke, that we may finiſh and abſolue the third point, as we haue done the two former. Thus the Pope departed with a great and pompous traine towards his Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, the Cardinals followed him, and the moſt part of them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him: but Cardinall <hi>Allen</hi> went home to his owne lodging, hauing ſome attendant vpon him, to watch &amp; ſée to him.</p>
                  <p>After they had well fed and filled their bodies with manie daintie cates and diſhes, the Pope and all the Cardinals came againe into the Conſiſtorie, and tooke their places as they had done before, when they were ſate, the Pope thus Orator-like debated with them.</p>
                  <p>In the forenoone (my louely Cardinals) we diſcuſſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triued fully and effectually two points which I propoſed vnto you:<note place="margin">The third point co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes.</note> Now it reſteth that we procéede likewiſe to the third and laſt, which is, whether the Engliſh Catholikes are to be main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained and farther retained, or elſe without longer delay, to be expelled and baniſhed. I ſay, and ſay againe, and maugre the ſtouteſt champion that liueth I will defend, that they are iuſtly to be baniſhed, and I will produce for it ſuch euident demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173816:14"/>
and alledge ſuch apparant reaſons, that you likewiſe ſhall both ſay it, and ſweare it: what thinke you of it couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cardinals?</p>
                  <p>Néeds muſt we (ſaid they) ſay and ſweare, as your holineſſe doth: eſpecially ſince you are led thereto with many weightie and great reaſons. I denie it (ſaid Cardinall <hi>Allen:</hi>) if they be exiled, they ſhall not iuſtly be exiled: I will neuer agrée to it, <hi>Dum ſpiritus hos regit artus:</hi> while I liue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Probo, probo,</hi> I will proue it (quoth the Pope:) yea, I will proue it ſo euidently, and ſhew it ſo expreſly that thou ſhalt not denie it, and therefore marke what I tell thée. Didſt not thou perſwade me in my laſt proceſſion, to take my iourney ſtraight forth, and to paſſe by the marble image of Dame <hi>Ioane?</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie it not (ſaid the Cardinall.) Note that (good Cardinals) quoth the Pope: you know what followed, and what a perilous agonie I was driuen into thereby: doth that deſerue nought I pray? Nay farther, haſt not thou detained monny that I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vnto thy countrimen? It is falſe, ſaid the Cardinall. Be not ſo obſtinate (quoth the Pope:) thine owne countrimen haue ſpoken and affirmed it. I doubt it, ſaid the Cardinall. Thou ſhalt finde it true (thou runnagate) quoth the Pope.<note place="margin">A proper kind of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</note> Doſt thou reproue me of a lie? O thou noiſome baggage: Dooſt thou ſnufe and ſcorne my power and authoritie, and diſdaine my words, that be of force to throw thée downe to the bottomleſſe pit of hell? Haue I deſerued this at thine hands (thou baniſhed brat?) well, well, thou ſhalt repent it, and that bitterly, for thou (thou curſt caterpiller) and thy cancred countrimen, haue brought more charges to me, then any other nation: haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed more troubles and hurleburlies to me, then any other nation, and haue deceiued and coſoned me more then any other Nation whatſoeuer. Trouble not your ſanctitie ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much (ſaid the Cardinall,) you cannot proue this you haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. I will proue it (thou ſcald begger) quoth the Pope, and I will rightly proue it, and therefore heare me (good faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Cardinals.) If there were no other thing that were of force lawfull and reaſonable, to make vs reiect and roote out the Engliſh fugitiues, yet the ſtrange and noiſome accident of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173816:14"/>
the woman Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> were ſufficient both to accuſe them of iniurie and infidelitie towards the holy citie of Rome, and alſo to expell them our of our regions and dominions for euer.<note place="margin">Vntruth, ſhe was a Dutch woman.</note> for ſhe was an Engliſh woman borne: and ſhée it is, and none but ſhe, that hath decayed and ruinated our high iuriſdiction, and brought ſuch a peſtilent downefall to our Apoſtolike regiment, that I feare me, with all our art, cunning, and policie, it will not be amended. Shall we fauour the ſtocke and genealogie of them that haue bene ſuch crackes and diſcredites to our power and authoritie? Shall we kéepe and maintaine them, that haue brought great perſecution, horrible confuſion and bloudie maſſacres to our truſtie and faithfull ſeruants? And ſhall not we eradicate and cut off thoſe Iudaſes, which cleaue to vs, and to our faith, onely for their owne gaine and refuge, and neuer do ſuch homage, ſeruice and obedience to our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, as is requiſite and expedient for them? O moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Cardinals, looke from the beginning that euer our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was profeſſed in England, and you ſhall ſée what ſmall zeale, loue, and affection it hath there receiued. And firſt looke vpon their kings and rulers, and you ſhall finde them to be the verie maules of the Romaine biſhops.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cambra</hi> the daughter of <hi>Belin,</hi> that married the Almaine prince, made long and ſharpe warre againſt this ſacred citie, and was like to ſpoile and ſacke it. So did <hi>Brennus</hi> the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Belin</hi> and others more, as we finde it recorded. King <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour,<note place="margin">Matthias Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſienſis. Anno. <hi>1094.</hi>
                     </note> vpon diſpleaſure conceiued againſt the high biſhop of Rome, ſaid, that no archbiſhop or biſhop of his realme, from thenceforth ſhould haue regard, either to the court of Rome, or to the biſhop thereof. King <hi>VVilliam Rufus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prohibition of going to Rome by king William Rufus. Anno 1098.</note> in his time would not ſuffer any of his ſubiects to go to Rome. What ſhall I ſpeake of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, who ſtayed the attempts of the Popes Legate, and made open complaint by his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour in the Councell of Lions in France, of him and his exactions: of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, who firſt renounced this Sée, and the ſupreme paſtour hereof: of king <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, who was the firſt that vtterly aboliſhed all our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and of the roiall maieſtie of quéene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173816:15"/>
now is,<note place="margin">
                        <p>God long preſerue her, and confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all her eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
                        <p>A famous learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who wrote diuers books and ſundrie inuectiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the church of Rome.</p>
                        <p>Laurence proued the Pope Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and Rome Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. An. 1290 Wickliffe a very learned man, liuing in the raigne of king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the 3.</p>
                        <p>Anno. 1371. who firſt manifeſtly diſcouered the Pope, &amp; maintained open diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt him.</p>
                        <p>Anno. 1581. <hi>Vide</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment of the Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, pag. 285.</p>
                     </note> the illuſtrate lampe and Phenix of all the world, the mother of Chriſtian Princes, and the verie Maul of me, and all my ceremonies? Looke vpon their biſhops and doctours, and you ſhall finde them to be blocks in our way, and the onely ſubuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our faith and dominion. What ſhall I tell you of <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted,</hi> ſometime biſhop of Lincolne, who wrote diuers inuectiues againſt the high biſhop <hi>Innocentius</hi> the fourth, and reproued manifold abuſes in the church of Rome, yea and ſaid, that this old verſe may be truly verified vpon it.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Eius auaritiae, totus vix ſufficit orbis,</l>
                     <l>Eius luxuriae, meretrix non ſufficit vna.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>The whole world doth ſcarſe ſatiſfie his couetouſneſſe, neither doth one harlot ſuffice for his leacherie. I omit to tell you of <hi>Laurence, Wickliffe,</hi> and an hundred other ſuch, who proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withſtood the biſhop of Rome, made open diſputation againſt him, called him Antichriſt, and Rome great Babilon. And as they haue earneſtly and eagerly withſtood and oppugned vs and our faith: ſo haue they euill entreated, and cruelly handled the profeſſours thereof. Héere I might tell you of <hi>Becket, Moore, Roffenſis,</hi> and manie others, how bitterly they haue béene vſed by them, and what torments and tortures they haue ſuffered for the profeſſion of our faith. I will come to men of later and freſher memorie, and to thoſe which with a falſe cloake and counterfait ſhew, haue deceiued our holineſſe, and brought our religion into miſerable contempt and obloquie. Who knoweth not the lewd pranckes and knauerie that <hi>Stukely</hi> that arrant vagabound, plaid of late with vs? Who knoweth not the bold preſumption, and diueliſh attempts of that mad and harebraind Sacramentarie, <hi>Richard Atkins,</hi> who rebuked the diſorder of our liues, proudly and heretically with ſplene and rancour, ſcorned, vpbraided, and vilified this grounded rocke of <hi>Peter,</hi> caught at the holy ſacrament, as the prieſt was carrying it, to haue throwne it downe, and héere in S. <hi>Peters</hi> church, threw downe the Chalice with the wine, and ſtriued to haue pulled the cake out of the prieſts hands. I could recite others vnto you, as <hi>Nichols, Munday,</hi> with manie more, who like peruerſe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites diſſembled to be conſtant Catholiques, and made external
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:173816:15"/>
ſhew thereof, but afterwards returning to their owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, reuolted, and wrote moſt curſed ſcandales and ſatyricall inuectiues againſt vs, and our Catholike faith, but for breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake I will omit them.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer, conſider (I pray) this exactly, how long hath that land reiected and diſallowed the Apoſtolike Romane religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ſyncere profeſſors thereof: and how vehemently doth it now roote and ranſacke it, and the zealous fauourers thereof? What land ſo much hindereth my procéedings, batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth downe my title and ſupremacie, and ouerthroweth the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fame and benediction of the Romane Church? What land ſo much vexeth and annoyeth my ſwéet and ſugred ſonne, <hi>Philip</hi> king of Spaine? What land ſo much helpeth and ſuccoureth the king of <hi>Nauerre</hi> fighting now for the crowne of France,<note place="margin">God giue him victorie ouer his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and quietly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh him in his kingdom</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy leaguers, my welbeloued children, and deuoted ſeruants? What land euerie kinde of wayes, ſtandeth ſo ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſtrongly againſt vs, and all our louing friends? Shall we harbour any inhabitants of that land? Shall we holder and ſuccour ſuch viperous broodes, and maintaine ſuch raſcall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques and libertines? No, no, <hi>Ferro &amp; flamma perdamus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Note the ſtomack and ſplene of the Pope.</note> let vs rather with fire and ſword deſtroy them: let vs no longer affect and fancie that rebellious nation: yea (noble Cardinals) let vs go vpon theſe adders and lions, and tread and trample them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our féete: let vs curbe and chaſtice them, and lay their honor in the duſt: and in ſo doing, <hi>ſaluus erit Petrus: ſalua erit eccleſia catholica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Cardinall <hi>Allen</hi> ſéeing the Pope ſo malcontent, and in ſuch extreame enuie and enimitie againſt him, and his countrymen, could no longer be ſilent, but this roundly vnlaced his mind.</p>
                  <p>Now do I find that true, which I counted but for a fable, that the greateſt clearkes be not commonly the wiſeſt men. Now I ſée that to be an oracle,<note place="margin">Polycraticon Iohannis Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisburienſis. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>26.</hi>
                     </note> which heretofore I thought but a méere cauill, that <hi>Roma non tam matrem exhibet, quàm nouercam:</hi> Rome ſheweth herſelfe not ſo much a naturall mother, as a ſtepmother, ſpoiling and deuouring her children, when they thinke ſhe moſt liketh and loueth them. Now do I know by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, thoſe words to be infallible veritie, which that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173816:16"/>
and learned doctour <hi>Eraſmus</hi> vſed, ſpeaking of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> vnto the councel of Carthage.<note place="margin">Inter Epiſt. Auguſt. Epiſt. <hi>91.</hi> Eraſ.</note> 
                     <hi>In hac Epiſtola, &amp; dictionem, &amp; ingenium, &amp; eruditionem, tali Praeſule dignam, cogimur deſyderare.</hi> In this Epiſtle, we miſſe both elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and wit, and learning, méete for ſuch a Prelate. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. O miſerie of mankind, I would my head were full of water, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares. Is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice now turned to wormewood, good vnto euill, ſwéete vnto ſowre, and light into darkneſſe? Are Catholikes become cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes, Prelates become Pilates, Philoſophers become <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and religious men become irreligious? Are ſmall théeues (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Socrates</hi>) led of great théeues to the gallowes? and are the verie heads and pillers of the church themſelues drowned in corruption, and infected with manie peſtilent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes? Why then, <hi>Nec Petrus, nec Paulus, quid ergo restat?</hi> Neither <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>Paul</hi> will helpe, what ſhall we doe? And muſt the Engliſh Catholikes be baniſhed,<note place="margin">They are iuſtly ſerued if they be ſo.</note> that haue forſaken their countrey, their goods, and friends, for the Romaine faith? Muſt they be expelled, who haue béene as faithfull, louing, and truſtie ſeruants to the ſea of Rome, as anie other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whatſoeuer? And muſt they be exiled that haue aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their liues,<note place="margin">If you had bene good ſubiects, you might haue liued at home.</note> and hazarded themſelues into millions of daungers for their zeale to their mother church, and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours thereof? Then let the Spaniſh, the French, the Iriſh, and the Scottiſh Catholikes be likewiſe exiled and pact out of Rome: for they are as iuſtly to be thus vſed as we, and as lawfully to be baniſhed as we are, and this I will proue. But <hi>Quidlibet est quodlibet in ſuo genere</hi> (as the Logicians ſay:) therefore I will firſt of all aunſwere the reaſons that haue béene obiected againſt vs by my high Lord and biſhop, leaſt in ſaying nothing I ſhould ſéeme to conſent, and ſo be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtir himſelfe to defend himſelfe, &amp; his countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note>The principall and chiefeſt thing that is laid againſt vs, is the woman Pope, Dame <hi>Ioane,</hi> who maketh no more againſt vs, then <hi>Laterane</hi> church doth when it hath one Engliſh man, or two in it. What though ſhe was an Engliſh woman? (and yet it is doubtfull whether ſhe was ſo or no.) What though
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173816:16"/>
ſhe was brought vp in mans apparrell? What though ſhe was Pope of Rome, with child, and deliuered thereof in proceſſion? What ſpot and crime is this to vs? What cauſe of baniſhment (I pray you heartely?) can we heale the ſore or quiet the ſlaunder? Hath it béene in our power to remedie the euill and aſſwage the miſchiefe? Was not ſhe fiue hundred yeares and more before this our time? Then truely, truely, we are for that no more to be baniſhed then the French are, becauſe their ancetours were ſometime like to ſpoile and ſacke the Capitoll: or the Italians are, becauſe <hi>Petrus</hi> the head Captaine of the citie of Rome, with two Conſuls and twelue Aldermen, and diuers other nobles, gathering their powers togither, laid hands vpon Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the fourtéenth, in the church of <hi>Laterane,</hi> and clapt him in priſon eleuen monethes.</p>
                  <p>Whereas it is farther obiected, that our kinges, Magiſtrates, and rulers, haue contemned and vilified the holy ſea of Rome, and haue verie ill entreated the Popes themſelues, with their Legates and faithfull ſeruants, and that none of our countrie haue done ſuch ſeruice, fealtie, and obedience to this bleſſed chair of <hi>Peter,</hi> as it was meete and requiſite for them: I will proue the contrarie, and that by ſuch cléere and euident teſtimonies, that you ſhal ſée the obiections againſt vs, flie away as the night clouds before the ſunne. What one of all our kings, before the time of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, but did fauour and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the holy Sea of Rome, did homage and duetifull obedience to it, and princely and honourablie fought in defence of it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Turkes and Infidels, and all other aduerſaries whatſoeuer? What a famous and ſingular king was <hi>Edgar?</hi> What a worthy maintainer of the catholike faith &amp; doctrine? He builded for religious monks <hi>48,</hi> monaſteries, or (as ſome report) as many as be ſundayes in the yeare. Did not king <hi>Iua</hi> after he had ruled the Weſt Saxons <hi>37.</hi> yeares go to Rome, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Monk, reſigning his kingdom to <hi>Ethelardus</hi> his Nephew?<note place="margin">Theſe kings became Monkes.</note> Did not the Quéene alſo <hi>Ethelburga</hi> become an Abbeſſe, ledde thereto with great and pure deuotion? Did not <hi>Ethereldus</hi> of Mercia, <hi>Kemedus</hi> of Mercia, <hi>Offa</hi> of Eaſt Saxons, <hi>Selly</hi> of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:173816:17"/>
Eaſt Saxons, and <hi>Sigebertus</hi> king of Eaſt Angles, do the like? Haue not manie Queenes, and kings daughters with other noble women become Nunnes, for the zeale and loue they had to the Apoſtolique faith of Rome? as <hi>Hilda, Ercheirgoda</hi> with her ſiſter <hi>Ermenilda,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Theſe Queens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes.</note> 
                     <hi>Edelberga, Werburga, Kinreda,</hi> &amp; <hi>Kinſwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> her ſiſter, <hi>Elfleda,</hi> with many others. What ſhall I tell you of king <hi>Canutus,</hi> who went to this holy citie on pilgrimage, and founded here an hoſpital for Engliſh pilgrims, and had ſuch loue and heartie affection to it, that he gaue to the Pope many preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gifts, and burthened his land with a yearely tribute, called the <hi>Romeſhot.</hi> I could tell you of many mo, but for breuitie I will ouerſlip them. What ſhall I ſpeake of many other excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent men which England hath nouriſhed and foſtered, who haue refuſed no paines, and forſaken no perils for the glorie and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of the Sea Apoſtolique of Rome?<note place="margin">
                        <p>He wrote a book againſt him, called <hi>Opus ſcintillae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Weakly and ſimplie God knoweth, as is to be ſeen. Traitors and conſpirators.</p>
                     </note> Shall I tell you of <hi>Lanfrancus</hi> biſhop of Canterburie, that confuted the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentarie hereſie of <hi>Berengarius:</hi> of the learned Abbot <hi>Petrus Cluniacenſis,</hi> that conuicted the doctrine of the <hi>Peterbruſians:</hi> of <hi>Thomas Walden,</hi> a moſt learned man, that wrote againſt <hi>Wickliffe:</hi> of the holie Biſhop <hi>Fiſher,</hi> that learnedly refuted <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp; <hi>Oecolampadius?</hi> Shall I tel you of Cardinal <hi>Poole, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner, Martin,</hi> and of others of later memorie, as <hi>Saunders, Cope, Briſtow, Dorman, Parſons, Morton,</hi> and of an hundred more, all which haue beene ſuch worthie proctours, and ſingular champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the Catholike religion, that no other Countrey hath yéelded and brought forth the like? For as that nation firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the fayth from Rome, ſo thoſe which are not fallen into the damnable bereſies of the Hugonetes, and other ſecrataries, do reuerence and obey the ſame, and for their conſcience will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide any croſſe and tribulation whatſoeuer. Saint <hi>Eleutherius</hi> Pope and Martyr, the firſt Apoſtle of Brytaine, preached in that land by <hi>Damianus</hi> &amp; <hi>Fugatius,</hi> within little more then <hi>100.</hi> yéers after Chriſts death. <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, that holie Pope, cauſed to be preached to the Engliſh nation, by <hi>Auguſtinus, Melitus,</hi> and other holy prieſtes: although the goſpellers that be there now denie this, and ſay, that as well the report of <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> as alſo of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that the one was the firſt Apoſtle of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173816:17"/>
Brittaines, the other of the Engliſh is vntrue: and blindly hold, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith was not firſt preached there by them,<note place="margin">the Goſpel came into England fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Eaſt, and not from Rome.</note> but either by <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathaea,</hi> or by <hi>S. Paul</hi> the Apoſtle paſſing that way in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Spaine, or by <hi>Simon Zelotes,</hi> or by the Gréeks, or ſome others.</p>
                  <p>But the Engliſh only you ſay, and none but they do hinder and annoy your ſacred and ghoſtly procéedings, and alſo ſubuert the good and gracious attempts of all your friends &amp; moſt loyall children. What is this to vs? They are gone from vs, they are not of vs, they are none of our fold, they are giuen ouer to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than: we haue forſaken them, we haue no ſocietie with them, we defie, damnifie &amp; deteſt them: we reuolt not, nor once ſo much as wauer: we ſtick wholly and ſolely,<note place="margin">A verie hote and earneſt proctor.</note> firmly &amp; fréely to the auncient Romane doctrine, and ſo we will do, come life, come death, come heauen, come hell, come fire, come ſword, come any croſſe or loſſe whatſoeuer. Shal we be for this our loue &amp; tender affection reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted? ſhal we be lopped off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this fruteful vine, as vnprofitable &amp; vnſauerie branches? ſhall we be baniſhed, and yet iuſtly conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of no crime or offence that deſerueth it? If we be, we muſt take it patiently: but truly we will ſay and ſay againe, <hi>iniusta nouerca: ſummum ius ſumma iniuria,</hi> an vnnaturall mother: great right, great iniurie. The Pope perceiuing his vehement allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; his tediouſneſſe therein, interrupted him with this chat. Ceaſe thy babling (Cardinal:) leaue off thy ands and ifs, &amp; tittle tattles I know not what: iwis, all not worth a blue point: much a do and litle helpe, fat féeding and leane cattell.</p>
                  <q>Hei miſero pingui macer eſt tibi taurus in aruo.</q>
                  <p>Thou kickeſt againſt the pricke, and caſteſt water into the ſea, and ſheweſt thy ſelfe not a Cardinall but a caitife, not a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke but a ſchiſmaticke, not an obedient child,<note place="margin">A graue and diſcreet rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of a Pope.</note> but a baſtardly and beggerly brat, ſo much to canuaſſe and cancell my words, to ſpurne at my celeſtiall and lawfull procéedings, and to go about to repel and obliterate my good purpoſe and determination. Haſt thou forgotten <hi>noſce teipſum,</hi> know thy ſelfe? Haſt thou cleane ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured my maieſtie and authoritie, my bell, booke and candle? Can I erre or be deceiued, or vtter any thing that is not legitimate &amp; hallowed? What ſhall I ſay to him, reuerend Cardinals? nay what ſhall I not ſay to him? But I ſée his infirmitie, therefore I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173816:18"/>
wil ſay no more to him, but do the déed. What ſay you to it? ſpeak ſhortly togither: are not the Engliſh lawfully to be baniſhed? The Cardinals forthwith replied: what more lawful and right? That which pleaſeth your holineſſe is autentique, and not to be any longer vrged or denied: your wil be done here in earth, as it is in heauen &amp; Purgatorie.<note place="margin">The Engliſh baniſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome. <hi>Sarci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas colligite Angli.</hi>
                     </note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quoth the Pope, <hi>Sic volo, ſic iubeo,</hi> I will &amp; command it ſo, but after this manner. Let proclamation now preſently be made in all parts of this citie, that al Engliſh Catholikes of what ſtate or calling ſoeuer they be, whether they be men, wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or children, do come to morow to S. <hi>Peters</hi> church, by nine of the clock in the forenoone, there to heare ſolemn maſſe, &amp; afterwards to depart away with bag &amp; baggage, &amp; ſuch goods as they haue, into ſuch countries as they ſhall thinke beſt: but not to inhabite or remaine within Italie, or any prouince therof, vpon paine of my curſe &amp; farther diſpleaſure.<note place="margin">Notable pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Pope indeed</note> The Cardinals anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Bleſſed are your words, &amp; ſupernatural be your cogitations: your diuine commandement with al reuerence ſhalbe executed. So the Pope aroſe, &amp; went to his Pallace, but the Cardinals tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ſomwhat longer behind, taking order for the proclamation: which being done, they went to their lodgings, &amp; Cardinal <hi>Allen</hi> with his accuſtomed guard went to his, where we wil leaue him maruellouſly diſtempered, yet ſomewhat buſily occupied in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king readie his trunkes, his Mules, &amp; other neceſſaries for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next day. The Proclamation being publiſhed, good God how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Engliſh Catholiks maruelled &amp; muttered at it, not knowing what ſhould be the cauſe therof.<note place="margin">The Engliſh greatly grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with their baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Some wept for ſorrow, ſome raged and rored like men at their wits end, ſome fell ſicke for ſorrow, &amp; euery one was not a little diſmaied, taking it both hardly &amp; heauily. Great was their griefe, ſtrange was their crie, &amp; wonderfull their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint: and one aboue the reſt, contemning the Pope, &amp; not broo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the iniurie, tooke his pen in hand, and wrote theſe verſes, and caſt them that night into the Popes Pallace.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Papè, proh papa perut pax, palma pudor<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>:</l>
                     <l>Praepinguis perſtat princeps, paſtor<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> peculí.</l>
                     <l>Pſeudopapa procul properato, pontificales</l>
                     <l>Putres peſſunda, proſpecta, ponito pyris.</l>
                     <l>Protomyſta pedes premito, pampilla, paletum,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:173816:18"/>Pauſa pauliſper, panchreſta<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> prouida phraende.</l>
                     <l>Proijce proſedas, preſſuras, proditiones,</l>
                     <l>Praelia praeſertim, praerancida pragmata paſſim.</l>
                     <l>Poſterga (praeſul) phantaſmata, pulpita, pupas,</l>
                     <l>Picturas, pedicas, putorem, praeſtigiaſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>,</l>
                     <l>Pellito praeſignem pompam, popaſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, popinas,</l>
                     <l>Peſtiferam petram, peltam, patinaſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> phalernum,</l>
                     <l>Pro praedis prauis, plenas perſoluito poenas.</l>
                     <l>Proh, peſtes, praxim, pugnas píceaſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> propulſa,</l>
                     <l>Poſce preces puras, pietatem porrige puram.</l>
                     <l>Plebeis populis praeſis, proſiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> potentèr.</l>
                     <l>Penſicula plagas Papatus, proluuium<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>:</l>
                     <l>Paſce pecus planè, plenè pete praedia petri.</l>
                     <l>Portentoſa patris poſtmitte piacula Pluti.</l>
                     <l>Propitio placido pro pneumaete, pace precare.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>An other alſo being as malecontent as the former, wrote theſe Sapphickes folowing
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Sancte Grégori potius ſceleſte,</l>
                           <l>Turges Grégori (maleſane papa,)</l>
                           <l>Perperàm tanta rabie, furore,</l>
                           <l>Bile, Britannis?</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Quod ſcelus (quaeſo) facinus quod illis?</l>
                           <l>Non tui Serui fuerint fideles?</l>
                           <l>Exulant ergo ſine lege Roma</l>
                           <l>Pignora chara?</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Tun' fidem Petri retines beatam?</l>
                           <l>Tun' tenes petram cathedram<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> Petri?</l>
                           <l>Vanitas. ſellam Sathanae ſuperbi</l>
                           <l>Iure capeſſis.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Iure tu Daemon, Deus ipſe nullo</l>
                           <l>Iure: peſſundas, violaſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> iura:</l>
                           <l>Iura quae toto Dominus colenda</l>
                           <l>Tradidit orbe.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Roma Grégori fugiemus? Eſto.</l>
                           <l>An tuos Anglos relegabis? Eſto.</l>
                           <l>Tunc vale ſcortum Babilonis, (excors Papa) valeto.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:173816:19"/>
When the next daie was come wherin they ſhould appeare in Saint Peters church, they (according to their holy fathers commandement) reſorted thereto, and there heard diuine maſſe, offering to our Ladie and to Saint George,<note place="margin">Babble a good, or elſe neither S. George nor our Lady wil heare you. Cardinall Alle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen.</note> and praying them, that they would chaunge and conuert the minde of the Pope, that they might continue in their Colledge and places as they had done tofore. When they had ſo done, Cardinal <hi>Allen</hi> called them together and ſpake thus: I neede not tell you (my deare and louing countrimen) what the cauſe is, that we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded hither. You knowe I am ſure by the proclamation yeſterdaie, that we are this daie to be baniſhed, according to the edict and decree of our holy Lord, <hi>Gregorie</hi> the xiiij. and his Cardinalles: the cauſe why (I promiſe you faithfully) I know not, neither any of you do know, as I coniecture: which is no ſmal griefe and dolor vnto vs: what ſhall we do (good countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?) Can you inuent no waie to remedie the matter, or at leaſt to pacifie it for a while vntill farther deliberation? They anſwered, we know none. Then (quoth the Cardinall) what ſay you to this? Some of the graueſt and moſt ſubſtantial of you ſhall goe with a Supplication to our holy father. VVe are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſaid they, if it maie any whit further vs. You ſhall (quoth the Cardinall) carie with you a thouſand Florens,<note place="margin">A Florene is an Italian crowne, of the value of iiij. <abbr>s.</abbr> vj. <abbr>d.</abbr> ſte. <hi>Roma dat om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, omnia dantibus.</hi>
                     </note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it vpon his holineſſe: three hundred of the which I my ſelfe will giue, and the reſt ſhall be collected among you. This much we will not onely now, but yearly hereafter giue vnto him, ſo that we maie haue licence and ſecurity here to inhabite, and this (no doubt) will doe the deede, and accompliſh our deſire. <hi>Iacta eſt alea</hi> (ſayd they) we like it well, let it be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed. Then they gathered the mony, and did put it together, and went with it to the Pope, and gaue him their ſupplication, the tenour wherof was after this maner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Engliſh mens ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to the Pope.</note>In moſt humble and obedient wiſe complaine vnto your holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, your poore afflicted and deſolate ſeruants the Engliſh Catholiques. VVheras it hath pleaſed your Highneſſe, together with your reuerend Cardinals for to renounce vs, to pronounce vs exiles and baniſhed, &amp; to cauſe a proclamation therof yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day to be publiſhed, that we ſhold all this day appeare at <hi>S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:173816:19"/>
church by nine of the clocke, and from thence directly to take our paſſage: we haue acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed (as we are moſt bounden) your good and gracious commandement, and we are all there preſent to attend your pleaſure &amp; authoritie. May it pleaſe you to haue ſome fatherly pitie and compaſſion vpon vs, that are far from our natiue countrey, and to tender our caſes ſo much, that we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue as we haue done heretofore, or elſe haue ſome lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger abode within your holy citie of Rome. VVe offer our ſelues proſtrate vnder the féet of your holineſſe with all that we are,<note place="margin">Wonderfull ſubmiſſion in the Engliſh.</note> and that we haue. Saue vs, kill vs, call vs, recall vs, approue vs, reproue vs, as you ſhall pleaſe: your voice (the voice of Chriſt in you ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king) we will acknowledge and reuerence: if we haue deſerued exile, we are contented: if death ſhall be layd vpon vs, it ſhall be moſt ſwéet and welcome: whatſoeuer your pleaſure and arbitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is or ſhalbe of vs, we recken it an heauenly felicitie. VVe haue brought with vs a thouſand Florens to beſtow vpon your holineſſe: and we haue all agréed, conſented and concluded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to pay ſo much yearly vnto you, if ſo be we may haue your ſacred licence &amp; permiſſion to remaine within this Citie. Accept therfore we beſéech you, this our petition: weigh and ponder our eſtate in an equall ballance: let not the ſentence of baniſhment go againſt vs: and in ſo doing, you ſhall find vs as true &amp; faithful vnto you, &amp; as louing &amp; truſty children, as any nation in Europe.</p>
                  <p>VVhen the Pope had ſéene this ſupplication, and perceiued the thouſand Florens, that they would then preſently and yearly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter giue vnto him: <hi>Bos in lingua,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Florens pacified the Popes anger.</note> his anger was ſomewhat miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, and the ſound and profound father was wholly ſatiſfied. For the Florens were the fragrant flowers that he deſired, the Saints that he honored, the fiſhes that he angled for, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> texts of ſcripture that he ſtudied vpon: yet to colour and cloke the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſpake this roundly vnto them.</p>
                  <p>My friends, your ſute is cold, &amp; your petition in vaine.<note place="margin">Note the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie of the Pope.</note> That which hath bene ratified, confirmed, and concluded by me and my Cardinals, cannot eftſoones be interdicted, or diſſolued, <hi>Sic Petrus, ſic iubet Eccleſia:</hi> there is now no remedie. <hi>Facta tranſacta omnia:</hi> The tide is paſt, &amp; the market ended: yet becauſe you ſhal know that I am your ſoueraigne Lord and gouernor, &amp; one that would
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173816:20"/>
gather his children togither, as the hen doth her chicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſtay here a while, &amp; I wil ſend with you one of my Secretaries to the reſt of your companie, and he ſhal declare vnto you more amply and fully my will, pleaſure, and determination. So he cauſed one of his Secretaries to come vnto him, &amp; taking him aſide, he ſhewed him his intent and purpoſe concerning the Engliſh Catholikes, willing &amp; commanding him to go with them to S. <hi>Peters</hi> church, to receiue their money, &amp; to giue them a <hi>quietus est,</hi> a full pardon and remiſſion of their ſinnes, and permiſſion to returne againe to their houſes and manſions. The Secretary went with them, and vttered this ſolemne Oration vnto them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Engliſh men.</note>My deare frends and good brethren, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort your ſelues, &amp; be of good chéere: for the caſe I can tell you is altered, &amp; you are againe receiued into fauor &amp; benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. How highly is God to be praiſed for that he hath prouided for his flock ſo good a ſhepherd, &amp; for his Church ſo wiſe &amp; prudent a Paſtor as <hi>Gregorie</hi> is. How greatly are you bound to him, who being Chriſts vicar &amp; chiefe deputie, <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor,<note place="margin">A worthy ſubſtitute, &amp; clawback for the Pope.</note> the Doctor of all Doctors, the father of al fathers, and the maſter &amp; teacher of all the world, ſo graciouſly prouideth for the health and welfare of his ſeruants, and carefully ſéeketh to aduance and promote the Catholike Romaine religion. O how louely and louingly doth he tender the caſes of you Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, &amp; how mercifully hath he dealt with you? He hath pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned your offences, and forgiuen your tranſgreſſions, he hath ſent me vnto you with his <hi>quietus est,</hi> with his Indulgence, and full abſolution of your ſinnes, yea, and with his ſacred fauour &amp; tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration to remaine in your former places and habitations.</p>
                  <p>Therefore <hi>Alleluya,</hi> praiſe ye our Lord: returne backe again, and do your duties accordingly. Hauing ended this ſpéech, the Engliſhmen thinking to haue an <hi>explodite,</hi> gaue a great <hi>plaudite,</hi> and ſaid,<note place="margin">The Engliſh returne to their vomite and to their wallowing in the myre.</note> 
                     <hi>Viuat Gregorius, Dominus Deus noster.</hi> The ſecretarie receiued the Florens, and tooke his leaue of them, returning to the ſwéete ſide of bleſſed <hi>Gregorie:</hi> the Engliſh fugitiues retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned backe againe with no ſmal ioy and contentation, being very ſhortly afterwards ſworne againe to the Romaine faith, and commanded to faſt twice a wéeke in remembrance thereof, for the ſpace of ſeauen yeares.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173816:20"/>
                  <p>THE ANATOMIE OF POPE IOANE, VVHEREIN HER LIFE, MANERS and death is liuely layd abrode and opened, and the forged cauils and allegations, that our aduerſaries vſe for her, throughly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripped and confuted: Neceſſarie for all thoſe that are not fully acquainted vvith the ſtorie, and not vnfrutefull to all them that loue and embrace the true religion of Chriſt, and abhorre the ſottish illuſions of Romish Antichriſt.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                     <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by Richard Field dwelling in the Blacke-friers neare Ludgate. 1591.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173816:21"/>
                  <head>TO THE REASONA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE READER.</head>
                  <p>THou haſt here mine Anatomie of Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> briefly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed: if not cunningly as it ought, blame mine inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: if not as an expert Chirurgian, impute the fault to want of skill, and not of good will. Howbeit, <hi>errare fortaſſis poſſim, haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus eſſe non poſſum.</hi> The matter hereof is ſo manifeſt, that <hi>cornu co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piae</hi> were needleſſe to poliſh it, and the truth ſo euident, that the Pumi-ſtone of exquiſit and ſuperficiall eloquence wold not haue bene requiſit to flouriſh and ſmooth it. Reade therfore willingly, iudge indifferently, and correct friendly. Let reaſon rule thee, authoritie moue thee, and truth enforce thee. And let vs both pray together, that the truth may be maintained, all errors confounded, and Gods name glorified. Fare-well.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:173816:21"/>
                  <head>THE ANATOMIE OF POPE IOANE.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I. How our aduerſaries the Papiſts are aſhamed of Pope Ioane, and how ſome of them do peremptorily denie the ſtory there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the ſcriptures are plaine to proue, the doctours and learned fathers plentifull to teſtifie: ſo manie and great are the ſignes and tokens which the Lord from time to time hath ſhewen, that Rome is Babilon, the Pope Antichriſt, the abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of deſolation, the archenimy of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.4.</note> and that man of ſinne, which lifteth himſelfe aboue all that is called God. Among which none ſurely is more liuely and euident, and more to be weighed and conſidered, then that of Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> which is ſuch a notable preſident and ſingular demonſtration thereof, that no man (vnleſſe wholly poſſeſſed of ſathan, and a verier beaſt then euer was <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi>) will doubt or put any diffidence therein. This is that which is the onely eyeſore, and biting coraſiue to our aduerſaries, which pulleth downe their proud peacocks feathers, and battereth their paper wals cleane to the ground. This is that which grieueth them to the gaules, and pricketh them to the quicke, which ouerwhelmeth them with horrour, and drowneth them top and taile in ſhame and diſhonour.<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi> Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati pudore, &amp; adoperti co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione diſcedunt.</note> For as the ſhamefull and deteſtable end of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> was ſuch a terrour and cooling card to his adherents, that they went away huſht, ouercome with ſhame, and couered with confuſion: ſo the ſtraunge euent of Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> and her oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious death, is ſuch a torment and torture vnto them, that in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173816:22"/>
their owne conſciences they are ſtinged and accuſed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to crye:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1.21.</note> 
                        <hi>Quomodo facta est meretrix vrbs fidelis? <hi>How is that faithfull Citie become a ſtrumpet?</hi>
                        </hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Anton. Par</hi> 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.7</note> 
                        <hi>Antoninus</hi> the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Florence, when he had opened this whole ſtorie of Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> was ſo aſtonied with the ſtraungeneſſe and admiration of the matter, that he cryed out: <hi>O altitudo Sapientiae, &amp; Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae Dei: quam incredibilia ſunt iudicia eius? <hi>O the depth of the wiſedome and knowledge of God, how incredible be his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes?</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <p>A ſtory wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, liuing in the time of king Edward the ſonne of Egelred, and Emma.</p>
                           <p>See Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus printed at Baſill, <hi>collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi> 407. <hi>Sub anno dom.</hi> 854. The author corrupted. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.17.</p>
                        </note>
                        <hi>Marianus Scotus,</hi> perceiuing what a déepe downfall and ruine this brought to the Sea of Rome, and that God would haue ſuch a matter openly knowne, to the euerlaſting deteſtation both of the perſon and place, writeth thus: <hi>Propter turpitudinem rei, &amp; muliebrem ſexum, Authores Pontificij huius Iohannae nomen non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt. <hi>Both for the ſhame of the matter, and alſo for the woman kind, the Popiſh Chronicles leaue out the name of Pope Ioane.</hi>
                        </hi> Can there be a more manifeſt toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then this, both of great cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of manners, and of diſſolution of life? Can there be a more infallible argument of open horror and filthineſſe, in that onely Sea aboue all others? Surely, ſurely, the Lord is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes, and all his iudgements are done in truth and equitie. But our aduerſaries haue a figgeleafe to couer this ſhame, and thinke by that, to ſhift and face out the matter, and to paſſe away inuiſible in a cloude. They flatly deny that there was euer any Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> in Rome,<note place="margin">A proper fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leafe of our aduerſaries to couer Dame Ioane</note> yea they ſtoutly &amp; ſturdily defende it, and ſay, that it is a fond and vaine fable, a lye, and a tale inuented of malice &amp; ſtomacke againſt them. Soft, and fayre, my Maiſters: your figgeleafe is drie and withered, and not worth a rotten figge, for it doth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer your ſhame, ſhew your nakedneſſe, and bewray your tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, and daſtardnes in the cauſe. You can not bridle the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Seas, nor blind the Sunne-beames, you haue as great an aduantage by the denying of it,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 3.21</note> as the <hi>Ebionites</hi> had by denying S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, and calling him an Apoſtata of the law. But can you prooue it ſo? Alas you can not: for your owne Doctors and Proctors, haue written and related it ſo plainely and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, that you muſt néedes (vnleſſe you clippe their credites, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173816:22"/>
deface them) confeſſe it.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohan.</hi> 8. <hi>muli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vt fertur.</hi> Teſtimonies for the profe of Pope Ioan <hi>vt dicitur.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Martinus Polonus</hi> the Popes Peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarie, and a Monke of the order of Ciſterce, who liued about the yeare of our Lord <hi>1320.</hi> hath written and reported it: So hath <hi>Platyna in Iohanne <hi>8.</hi> Sabellicus, Enneadis <hi>9.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> Marianus Scotus. Rauiſius Textor in Officina. Antoninus</hi> the Archbiſhop of Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. <hi>Supplementum Chronicorum. Chronica Chronicorum. Faſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus temporum,</hi> and others mo. Are all theſe lyars and tale tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers? Are the writings of all theſe men fabulous and vntrue? I truſt you will not ſay ſo. Then giue place vnto the trueth, and kicke not ſtill againſt the ſpurre: for the truth is great,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 4.</note> and will preuaile, and will ye, nill ye, it will conquere. Deny not ſuch a miraculous token, ſhewing as it were in a glaſſe, the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and abhomination of the Romaine Church, and of the Pope thereof, the open aduerſarie of God, and the abhomination ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the holy place. Acknowledge and confeſſe it, and let the remembrance thereof worke ſuch repentance and remorſe in you, that you may renounce your errors, abiure your hereſies, forſake the kingdom of darkneſſe, and ſerue the Lord in true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſneſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. II. How ſome of our aduerſaries goe about to excuſe and ſhift the matter, by poſſibility of nature, ſaying, that Pope Ioane might be Hermaphroditus, that is, a man and woman both in one.</head>
                     <p>THe Lyon is knowne by his clawes, the Leoparde by his ſpots, and our aduerſaries by their peruerſe &amp; corrupt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to defend Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> and to colour her filthineſſe and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination withall: wherein as many of them haue toyled and moyled not a little, ſo eſpecially hath one <hi>Cope</hi> our Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, an earneſt Proctor for the Pope and his Prelates, who writing of this matter, ſayth thus:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Neque hic ego quicquam dico de Hermaphroditis &amp;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dialogo.</hi> 1. <hi>Pag.</hi> 47.</note> 
                        <hi>de quibus veterum libri pleni ſunt. <hi>I will here ſay nothing of ſuch perſons, as be called Hermaphroditi, and are both man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man all in one, whereof in old writers we find much mention.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Meaning thus in effect, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope might be <hi>Hermaphoditus,</hi>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:173816:23"/>
an <hi>Herkinalſon,</hi> that is to ſay, a man and a woman both in one: and thinking by this meanes ſomwhat handſomly to excuſe and ſhift the matter. Gentle ſtuffe for the nonce; and worthy diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie for ſuch a Romaine courtier. What toy is there ſo vaine and ridiculous, and what excuſe ſo childiſh and friuolous, which they will not force to ſerue their turne?<note place="margin">Ouid. Meta. <hi>4.</hi> Salmacis fons ſemiuiros facit.</note> The Pope may be a man and a woman both in one verie likely, for he might perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture waſh himſelfe in the fountaine <hi>Salmacis</hi> in <hi>Caria,</hi> and be made halfe a man: or he might perchance embrace a woman as the Nymph did,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Metam.</hi> 4.49.</note> finding <hi>Hermaphroditus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> naked, and deſire of the gods as ſhe did, that of them two might be made one bodie. Is not this Catholike Theologie, and apoſtolike diſcipline méete for a Romaine cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion? Is not this credible and to be iuſtified? Yes no doubt, for the Pope that is a God &amp; aboue Angels, may tranſforme himſelf if it pleaſe him,<note place="margin">Cor. Agrippade Occul. Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>45.</hi>
                        </note> as well as <hi>Proteus, Periclimenus, Achelous,</hi> and <hi>Metra</hi> the daughter of <hi>Eriſichtho,</hi> and may &amp; can do grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miracles then theſe: for in his hands is heauen, hell, and purgatorie, he hath all the earth at his commandement, all the ſaincts at his commandement, yea, and all the diuels too if néed be. Therefore a ſmall matter it was for him, and the leaſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of a thouſand, to make himſelfe a man and a woman both in one. What curſed doctrine is this? alas what a childiſh and ſillie excuſe is this, to couer Dame <hi>Ioanes</hi> infamie, and to bring her to ſome credite in the world? O miſerable and phantaſticall imaginations, of verie heathen Atheiſts &amp; Apiſtes not allowed nor maintained.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> For ſhame, for verie conſcience ſake, for the regard of the world, and for feare of Gods heauie wrath, reiect ſuch fooliſh dreames and ceremonies, and vphold no longer ſuch blind and vaine excuſes, in defence of that which is ſo well and perfectly knowne to the world, and which is ſuch a cleare light, and plaine ſignification of ſacriledge, ſuperſtition and idolatrie in the Romaine ſea. Let not Antichriſt any longer deceiue you, nor the Romiſh Babilon infect you with her poiſoned cuppes.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ierem.</hi> 2.13.</note> Damne not vp the ſprings of the water of life, nor breake vp puddles of your owne, ſuch as are able to hold no water, but ſerue the Lord with feare, and reioice vnto him with reuerence;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:173816:23"/>
embrace his word, loue him, and put your whole truſt in him: then you ſhall be his people, and ſhéepe of his paſture, then your leafe ſhall not wither, yea and then looke whatſoeuer you ſhall doe, it ſhall proſper.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. III. How ſome ſay, that the Pope being a man, may afterwardes be chaunged into a woman.</head>
                     <p>GReat is the ſubtiltie, and merueilous is the craft that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than vſeth to drowne men in hereſie, to thruſt them head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into ſinne and perdition, and to make them obſtinately wallow and welter therein. He will prouide for them ſuch fine excuſes: he will get for them ſuch ſtarting holes and defences, that they ſhall thinke themſelues ſecure, to be in the right way, and to ſtande vpon good and firme ground, when it is farre otherwiſe: yea he will leaue no meanes vnaſſayed to kéepe them in his ſubiection, and to make them drunken with their owne erronious opinions. This may be perceiued in none more perſpicuouſly then in the Papiſtes, and in no one thing more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly, then in their defence of Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> whom the diuell hath ſo bewitched, ſo blinded, and ſo wedded to their owne ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willes, that to couer her deformitie, and to paint it out with ſome colour to the worlde, they haue ſpredde themſelues againe as the heauens, and left no way vnattempted. Wherefore let vs goe further, and ſée more of their dealing, and more of their fetches in the matter: and let vs come againe to <hi>Cope,</hi> and ſée what a good and ghoſtly Maſter he is for his Dame <hi>Ioane.</hi> After he had ſayd, that the Pope might be an <hi>Hermaphroditus;</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth not there, but going further, he forceth <hi>Ouids Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſis</hi> to ſerue his turne, and ſayth, that the <hi>Pope being a man, may be chaunged into a woman:</hi> for theſe be his wordes. <hi>Et ne à noſtri temporis memoria longius abeam, non ignoro monumentis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terarumeſſe traditum. Mulierem quandam nomine Aemyliam An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio Spenſae, Civi Eubulano nuptam, post duodecimum à nuptijs an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in virum transijſſe. Legi etiam alteram multerem, vbi puerum peperiſſet, in marem fuiſſe mutatam.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:173816:24"/>
                        <hi>But not to go farther then the remembrance of our owne time: I know that it is written that a certaine woman named Emylia, married vnto one Antonius ſpenſa a Citizen of Eubulum, ten yeares after ſhe had bene married, was turned into a man. I haue likewiſe read of another woman, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe had bene brought a bed, afterwards became a man.</hi> Certes this is ſtrange for a man to be turned into a woman: but all things well conſidered, it is nothing ſtrange at all. For the Pope hath all lawes and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge within his breſt, and whatſoeuer he be, he is holy, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate, and can worke no ſmal wonders. May not he change himſelfe into ſundrie ſhapes, as wel as <hi>Iupiter, Mercurie, Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> and other of the Gods? May not he be changed into a woman as well as <hi>Tireſias</hi> was:<note place="margin">Metam. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Pontanus.</note> or as well as <hi>Caietana</hi> and <hi>Aemilia</hi> into men? Yes doubtleſſe, for he is farre aboue them, and can do much more then euer they could. Therefore maſter <hi>Copes</hi> ſurmiſe, that the Pope may be changed into a woman, is verie Catholike and ſubſtantiall, and fit for ſuch a pregnant and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate doctour. But fie for ſhame, what a ſottiſh excuſe is this? VVhat a vaine illuſion and Maygaine? Is there no better ſhift nor ſurer refuge then this? Is there no thicker cloud to ſpread ouer the matter with more likelihood? Then who ſéeth not the bondage of Egypt: who ſées not the ſpirituall Babilon, and the madneſſe of them that commit ſpirituall fornication with her? Better it had béene, and the ſafer way by a great deale, ſimplie and plainly to haue confeſſed it, then by a myracle to turne the Pope from a man into a woman, and that which is worſt of all, obſtinately to defend it. For now euerie one doth ſée, that you had leifer be filthie ſtill, then leaue off your filthineſſe, and had rather (becauſe you loue your vices) <hi>Excuſare, quàm excutere,</hi> Excuſe them, then forſake them: and as many as in ſpirite and truth do loue the Lord, do mourne for griefe, to ſée men carried ſo headlong with ſuch godleſſe and retchleſſe imaginations.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:173816:24"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IIII. How they haue left out Pope Ioanes name out of their Calendar: and how they haue hired Onuphrius Pamuinius of ſet purpoſe to face out the matter.</head>
                     <p>SOme of our aduerſaries take this <hi>Enthememe</hi> for an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:<note place="margin">An Enthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meme of our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to denie Pope Ioane.</note> 
                        <hi>Dame Ioane is not regiſtred</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                        <hi>Cale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dar among the Popes: <hi>Ergo</hi> it is but a vaine fable that euer dame Ioane was Pope in Rome.</hi> The conſequent is very ſimple, &amp; not to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe it is well knowne, that the biſhops names as wel in Rome, as in other places, haue vpon ſundrie occaſions béene of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes quite ſtriken out of the Calendar. But dame <hi>Ioanes</hi> name (they ſay) is not in their Calendar. It may be ſo: &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray? <hi>Martinus Polonus,</hi> one of their owne ſworne bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, doth tell vs. <hi>Iohanna</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>non ponitur in Catalogo Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificum ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propter muliebre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſexum, quàm propter deformitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facti. <hi>Pope Ioane is not reckoned in the Calendar of the holy Popes, as wel for that ſhe was a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as alſo for very ſhame of the matter.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The like doth <hi>Sabellicus</hi> ſet downe.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ennead.</hi> 9. <hi>lib.</hi> 1 <hi>Pag.</hi> 469.</note> 
                        <hi>Nullus defunctae honor ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus: fama tenet, ob tam foedae rei memoriam. <hi>There was no honour beſtowed at her buriall: the report is, for the remembrance of her filthie act.</hi>
                        </hi> By this we ſée, that the name of Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> was not put into the Calendar of the Popes, partly becauſe ſhe was a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſpecially, becauſe ſhe was a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch a filthy life, &amp; vicious behauiour.<note place="margin">In Scholijs in Platynam.</note> Therfore this reaſon of our aduerſaries is a blind coniecture, &amp; of no force. But (they ſay) <hi>Onuphrius Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinius</hi> vpon <hi>Platina,</hi> hath truely &amp; learnedly written hereof: &amp; he that liſt to read that diſcourſe of his, ſhal eaſily beléeue the whole matter to be fabulous. Truth it is, that ſuch a one indéede hath of late written thereof, and beaten his braines not a little to helpe out this matter, but all in vaine: for he was one of the Popes Paraſites, hired and procured by him onely for that buſineſſe. His booke was printed in Venice, and plauſiblie accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his friends and welwillers: but the ſtuffe that he hath brought in there, to make the world beléeue, that there was neuer any Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> in Rome, is ſuch traſh &amp; ſo ridiculous, that it will grieue a good Chriſtian in his heart, to read and ſée it.</p>
                     <q>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:173816:25"/>
                        <l>Quid non mentiri, vel quid non protinus audet</l>
                        <l>Fingere mortale ingenium, vt ſibi maior eundi</l>
                        <l>In praeceps pateat via, liberior<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> potestas</l>
                        <l>Peccandi detur, minus &amp; peccata pudoris</l>
                        <l>In ſe contineant?</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>This is the craft and policie of the Pope, to hire &amp; procure men to ſmooth and ſooth his matters, and to face and grace out his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties, with many forged lies &amp; falſe ſuppoſitions: thinking by that meanes, to dazel mens eyes, and to make them beléeue they be true, godly, and apoſtolical. This haue many popiſh Pages of late done,<note place="margin">Moſt impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and liers</note> and eſpecially <hi>Amphilochius, Onuphrius, Surius,</hi> and <hi>Hieronimus Bolſecus,</hi> one that hath vſed moſt ſhameleſſe ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, moſt vile, ſpiteful, and horrible lies and cauils, with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate and vnciuile bitterneſſe, procéeding from the vnſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and vnquiet humour of his heart, againſt the godly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend miniſters of the goſpel, <hi>Caluin, Beza,</hi> with others moe. God of his mercie graunt, that they may repent and amend their liues, renounce their damnable errors, forſake their curſed ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and not aduenture their wits in ſuch deſperate cauſes. For, <hi>Nemo periculoſiùs peccat, quàm qui peccata defendit. <hi>No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinneth with more danger, then he that ſtandeth in defence of ſinne.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. V. VVhat yeare of the Lord Pope Ioane liued in Rome. How long ſhe was Pope: and betweene what Popes ſhe was.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Herodotus.</note>
                        <hi>XErxes</hi> the great king of Perſia, when he brought ouer his huge armie into Grecia, ſent out his letters of defiance, vnto the great mount Athos that is in Macedonia, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to ſtand ſtill, and not to ſtirre a foote, nor to worke any diſpleaſure, either to himſelfe, or to his armie. Euen by like authoritie, and with as good diſcretion, the Pope and his hyrelinges, haue done with dame <hi>Ioane,</hi> who being able no kind of way, to colour or cloake her ſufficiently, haue ſent out their letters and defiance to all Countreyes and Regions that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly knowe her, commanding them not once to ſpurne or kicke againſt her, nor ſo much as to make any record or mention of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:173816:25"/>
her. But let them wraſtle and wrangle ſo much as they will, let them curſe &amp; defie while they liſt, and let <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> and all the rabble rout of them do what they can, the truth thereof will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be forgotten: it is and will be abſolutely knowne, to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion of proud Antichriſt, and to the euerlaſting execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the popiſh and péeuiſh ſynagogues. For although they haue left the name of Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> out of the Calendar of the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome, onely for ſhame,<note place="margin">What the cauſe was, that they haue left Pope Ioane out of their Calendar.</note> leaſt it ſhould appeare in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords that a woman, &amp; ſuch a woman had béene biſhop of Rome, or that the biſhop of Rome had béene with child: and although they neuer ceaſe to bolſter and bungle vp the matter, ſometime with this ſhift, ſometime with that, ſometime affirmatiuely, ſometime negatiuely: yet ſo many Chronicles would not haue recorded it, nor ſo many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would haue written it, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world would ſo vniuerſally haue beléeued theſe things of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pope, more then of any other, had it not beene true, credible, and veritie. For where I pray bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hiſtory of her firſt? In Rome. From what place was it firſt publiſhed abroad into the world? From Rome. What be they that haue written and declared it? The truſtie friends of Rome: yea the great autenticall doctours and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Pope, haue deſcribed and auouched it, ſome li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing foure hundred yeares agoe, ſome fiue hundred, who haue euer béene counted famous fathers in Rome, and worthy of no ſmall authoritie and reuerence. What yeare of our Lord was dame <hi>Ioane</hi> Pope in Rome? As they haue written, 853. How long was ſhe in the Popedome? As they haue written, two yeares, one moneth, and foure dayes. Betwixt what Popes was ſhe? As they themſelues haue written, betwéene <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Benedict</hi> the third. Séeing then that our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries owne friends and Proctours haue written and related it, and ſo plainly and expreſly ſhewen it, I maruell much with what faces any of them can denie it, or go about to excuſe it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:173816:26"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VI. What Pope Ioanes name was, how ſhe was not borne in England, but at Mentz in Germanie, and how ſhe came to Rome, and to the Popedome.</head>
                     <p>MAny there be (I know) and thoſe our owne countrimen, who thinke and beléeue dame <hi>Ioane</hi> to be an Engliſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man borne. I can coniecture no other thing to be the cauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of but report onely, being for the moſt part more common then true,<note place="margin">The cauſe why Pope Ioane is thought to be an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh woman borne.</note> and eſpecially becauſe in manie authors entreating of this matter, is found, <hi>Iohannes Anglicus,</hi> or <hi>Iohannes de Anglia,</hi> which ſéemeth vnto them to be tranſlated, <hi>Iohn an Engliſh man,</hi> or <hi>Iohn of England.</hi> Becauſe I would haue all thoſe that be not as yet truely certified and reſolued herein, to agrée togither and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to beleeue this point, I will declare vnto them the truth of the matter,<note place="margin">Why ſhe was called Ioane Engliſh.</note> according to the opinions of the beſt and moſt approued writers. She was called <hi>Ioane Engliſh</hi> by the ſurname of her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and borne at Mentz in Germany. <hi>Martinus Polonus</hi> the Popes ghoſtly Penitentiarie, diſcourſing at large of this matter affirmeth the ſame, for thus he writeth. <hi>Iohannes Anglicus, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Maguntinus, ſedit annos duos, menſem vnum, dies quatuor, &amp;c. <hi>Iohn Engliſh (ſo ſurnamed) borne at Mentz, ſate in the Romaine Sea two yeares, one moneth, and foure dayes. Theodoricus Nie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>
                        </hi> alſo, ſometime the Popes Secretarie, and therefore had good cauſe to know the truth hereof, doth liuely paint out the whole matter, and expreſly ſheweth the ſame. <hi>Et fuit mulier de Maguntia nata, quae ſtuduit Athenis ſub virili habitu: &amp; in tantum profecit in artibus, vt tandem veniens Romam per biennium in ſchola Artes liberales legerit: &amp; adeo ſufficiens fuit, vt etiam Maiores &amp; Nobiles vrbis eius lectiones frequenter audiuerint. Et postea eligitur in Papam &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And there was Ioane a woman, borne at Mentz, and had ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died at Athens in the apparell of a man, and had ſo profited in the Artes, that at laſt comming to Rome, two yeares together ſhe profeſſed the liberall Sciences in a Schoole. And her gift in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was ſuch, that the Elders and Nobles of the Citie reſorted of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to heare her reade. Afterward ſhe was choſen Pope, &amp;c.</hi> We
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173816:26"/>
néede not cite any more teſtimonies for farther proofe hereof:<note place="margin">Pope Ioane a Dutchwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man borne.</note> theſe two doe manifeſtly ſhewe, that ſhe was a Dutchwoman borne, and not called <hi>Ioane</hi> Engliſh by the name of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, for that ſhe was an Engliſh woman borne in England (as many imagine) but only by the ſurname of her father. For who knoweth nor that there are many at this day called by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> names of Scot, Iriſh, French, Welſh, Norman, Gaſcoyne Holland, and yet not borne in any of theſe Countries, but onely in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande. Therefore it is true, and without all doubt, that Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> was not borne in England but in Germany. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome there be (whoſe authoritie is verie credible and ſufficient) that ſay her name was <hi>Gilberta,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Her right name was Gilberta, but called Ioane the eight. Pope Ioane was a ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at Athens.</note> and called <hi>Ioan</hi> the eight: who likewiſe affirme, that ſhe was a Dutch-woman of Mentz, and went with an Engliſh Monke, out of the Abbey of Fulda to Athens, in mans apparell. Well, truth it is, that ſhe was in the young yeares of a girle brought to Athens, by one that was her louer in mans apparell. There ſhe ſtudied, and profited ſo much in diuerſe ſciences, that none were found to be compared with her. This is not ſtraunge,<note place="margin">Women brought vp in mens ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, and taken for men.</note> nor much to be marueiled at: For <hi>Rauiſius Textor in Officina,</hi> writeth the like of one <hi>Marina,</hi> that diſſembling what ſhe was, liued many yeres in an Abbey as a Monke: &amp; of <hi>Laſthenia, Axiothea,</hi> and others, that being women, came into the Schoole in mans apparell to heare <hi>Plato.</hi> The like doth many others write of <hi>Euphroſyna</hi> that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mayde, that dwelt <hi>36.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pope Ioane came to Rome. She was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Pope of Rome. Her behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in that high office. A moſt liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſident of the who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Sea.</note> yeares in Monkes apparell among Monkes, and was neuer otherwiſe taken then for a Monke.</p>
                     <p>From Athens ſhee came to Rome, and there profeſſed learning openly, and had great Doctors to her Schollers, and for opinion of learning and good life by one conſent of all, was made Pope: being in this high and glorious ſeate, ſhe behaued her ſelfe ſo orderly, and diſcharged that ſupernall office ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, that ſhe was with child, and as ſhe went in Proceſſion deliuered thereof, and ſo dyed. Thus was the Pope of Rome, who is ſuch a parls fellowe that he can not erre, a woman with child, deliuered in proceſſion, dead openly in the ſtréetes, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried without any honour or ſolemnitie. God giue all Chriſtians grace by this example to beware of the Antichriſtian and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonicall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:173816:27"/>
Pope, to renounce him, and all his errors, to reiect him and all his Paraſites, and to ſée the trueth and that bleſſed hope wherevnto they haue béene called, ſo as they may glorifie him alone, who is the true God, and alſo that ſame Ieſus Chriſt whom he ſent downe to vs from heauen, to whom with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the holy Ghoſt be giuen all honour and glorie euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
